<zodiacs>
    <!-- Add real month names here  //blueCommand -->
    <zodiac month="1" img="zodiac0" name="Unodin">Unodin signifies the beginning of the Yliakum calendar year and for newfound fortitude for the coming months.  It is at this time that the workers in the fields begin planting their crops.  This month epitomizes the beginnings of life and represents the will needed to persevere.  Deshiin, the sign of the Steady Hand, tells those born under its influence that they are strong of will which sometimes blinds the intelligence needed to make sound decisions.</zodiac>
    <zodiac month="2" img="zodiac1" name="Byari">Byari, the second month in the Yliakum calendar, is the time of festivals and rejoicing as the many Peoples celebrate Ierefal, or The Coming.  It is recorded in ancient history that the various races began to appear in Yliakum at about this time of year.  Twivenis, the Verdant Wings, personifies the swiftness needed to survive in this new world while having reduced vitality and vigor due to the nature of travelling the Great Portals.</zodiac>
    <zodiac month="3" img="zodiac2" name="Treman">Treman, the third month in the Yliakum calendar, symbolizes the transition to watchfulness and personal growth.  In order for the first People to get along with one another in this new place they concentrated on their newfound common ground instead of clinging to their individual pasts.  People born under Vooreva, the sign of Unified Vigilance, possess the unique gifts of persuasion and easier access to the magic most directly tied to the Azure Sun.  As counterpoint, the sacrifices needed for unity put a drain on an individual's will, in support of the greater good.</zodiac>
    <zodiac month="4" img="zodiac3" name="Kravaan">The month of Kravaan is the peak of the year, with enhanced plant growth throughout.  Trees crowd together and stand as testament to the solidity of Yliakum's lush existence.  Those born under the sign of Dohdeth, the Leaf of Fate, enjoy an enhanced resilience, but lack finesse and grace, much like the immobile forest they embody.</zodiac>
    <zodiac month="5" img="zodiac4" name="Quintahl">Quintahl, the fifth month in the Yliakum calendar year, is representative of the winding down of the crops' growth and festival planning.  Harvest is always a time of celebration, and the Peoples of Yliakum plan decadent parties laden with food and gifts.  The sign of Taarev the Hunter embodies the speed and accuracy required to hunt game in the wild, as well as being adept with small blades.  Taarev would tire easily, however, and that limitation is passed on to those born under his sign.</zodiac>
    <zodiac month="6" img="zodiac5" name="Azhord">Azhord signifies the end of the growth season and the beginning of Harvest.  This sixth month of the Yliakum calendar brings the Visions of the historic Seers to light as all People look to their past for guidance in their future.  Divination is stronger in those born under Azriim's pearly influence, and increased mental faculties are inherited from the Seers of old.  As physical prowess was historically not one of their strong points, people under Azriim's power have limits to their own.</zodiac>
    <zodiac month="7" img="zodiac6" name="Ylaaren">The month of Ylaaren is the end of Harvest and the time when Yliakum turns a bit cooler.  Natural vents in the cavern roof leak cold air that drifts heavily downward into the heart of the cone.  People born in the time of Firannis the Warrior gain additional strength in anticipation of the changing season.  Strength does not impart wisdom, however, which was the downfall of Firannis himself, a lesson often taught to younger children.</zodiac>
    <zodiac month="8" img="zodiac7" name="Dwanden">Dwanden, the eighth month of Yliakum, is marked by the annual formation of hoarfrost on the lower levels of Yliakum.  Great furnaces were built in ancient times to provide warmth to the Peoples, both on solid ground and in the water.  Steam begins appearing on the lake's surface as the furnaces below warm the watery environment for its denizens.  Those born under Goreld's sign, that of the Great Forge, possess greater endurance and have a knack for using a forge to repair things, but gruff attitudes carried by those who disliked the cold weather are instilled in those born with Goreld's favors. </zodiac>
    <zodiac month="9" img="zodiac8" name="Novari">The cold month of Novari brings frigid temperatures in the beginning, but a slight warming trend late in the month.  Hoarfrost has thickened to resemble something that some races refer to as snow.  Some ice flakes fall from the small vents in the cavern roof and settle on the upper levels, which begin to melt off as Novari draws to a close.  Cheliss, the sign of Frostflow, symbolizes the Great Melt that occurs at the end of the month, swelling the lower lake to the edge of the Sixth.  Those born under Cheliss' power find themselves in possession of a colder logic that helps them excel in matters of the mind, but suffer an intolerance of others that leads them to lesser paths of wisdom.</zodiac>
    <zodiac month="10" img="zodiac9" name="Yndoli">Yndoli, the tenth month in Yliakum calendars, signals the end of the cold season and the general warming of the climate in the cone.  Avian creatures take to the skies and animals begin their mating rituals, while many beasts shed their old skins and grow in their new natural armors.  The sign of Karkath the Beast Lord enhances the natural ability of one to make a favorable impression on those encountered, as mating hormones tend to make one more desirable, but also lowers the reasoning ability of many intelligent creatures.</zodiac>
</zodiacs>
