<?xml version="1.0"?><!-- Credits for this help file: acraig, aiwendil, magodra, talad, weltall, Venalan, and Taya. --><help>

    <branch name="START HERE"><Contents><content type="text">Welcome to the PlaneShift Help Guide. In this first section you may find all the tips provided in the tutorial area, covering the basic functions of the game.</content></Contents>
<topic name="Movement">
<Contents><content type="text">You can move around by pressing the keys W (forward), S (backward), A (rotate left), D (rotate right), Q (strafe left), E (strafe right), R (run).

If you are left-handed and find these options difficult to use you can change them by opening the 'OPTIONS' window in the toolbar and choosing 'CONTROLS' and then 'KEYS'.

Move this window a bit to the side of the screen, so you will be able to better see your character. Without closing this window, practice moving by using the A, W, S, and D keys.

You have now practised basic movements. Here are a few more: press the spacebar and you will see your character JUMPING. Now hold down the left shift key while moving and you will see your character RUNNING forward or backward.

If you want to LOOK AROUND press the middle mouse button (or alternatively press the TAB key once to turn it on and press Tab again to exit mouse look mode). In this mode you can move your mouse to have your character rotate left or right and look up and down.

You can change the POINT OF VIEW by pressing 'm'. Press it a few times to cycle through 'free movement', 'dynamic follow', 'free rotation' and 'first person' points of view, moving your character each time. Then go back to 'third person follow' mode. This is probably the best one to use for the tutorial.</content></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="Interacting with NPCs">
<Contents><content type="text">You can interact with both players and NPCs.

When you right-click (ctrl-click for Mac users) or left-click an NPC or player this is called 'targeting' and a red marker will appear under the selected person/NPC/object. Left-clicking just selects the character, while right-clicking opens up a new interaction menu with actions you can choose.

Without closing this window, try to right-click the character you just approached. A set of icons will appear, such as Attack, Trade/Give, Examine, Buy/Sell, and Talk. The red 'X' icon just cancels your right-click selection without performing an action on the character. You can also select yourself and choose Examine.

To TALK to any NPC, target them, and then right-click and select the TALK/LIPS icon. This will open the 'Quest menu window'. Any possible quest options are shown in individual bubbles. You can select those options by CLICKING ON them. Be on the lookout an arrow in the middle of the screen which you can click to go to the next page of options. The 'free text' input will be visible on every page you go to.

When an NPC is talking to you if you want to skip forward in the text you can click on the text bubble showing the NPC talking. You should be careful about skipping forward as you might miss important information the NPC tells you.

TALK/LIPS Button.</content><content type="pic" src="ButtonSpeak;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
To leave the Quest menu at any time you can click on the 'BYE' button.

USING FREE TEXT (manually typed words):

The free text input bubble is used to write/say text of your choice to an NPC to either answer a specific question asked of you in a Quest, or to ask the NPC a personal question.

You can ask any NPC in the game things such as 'Hello.' 'How are you?' or 'Who are you?' and they should give you a personal response. The response will appear on screen in speech bubbles, and once the NPC is finished, the quest options and free text option will reappear.

There might be cases when a quest bubble says something like "I know the answer to: Type in the name of the weapon you want." This means that the NPC requires a free text answer to progress the quest. At this point you can just type your answer into the text entry box which appears each time you open the quest menus. Or, you can click the bubble with the quest which will remove all other menu bubbles and leave you with just the free text bubble for you to give your answer.

You can also talk to an NPC without using the Quest bubbles. To do this, target an NPC, select the NPC tab in the chat window, and then type what you want to say in the chat window. When you use this method the responses will only appear in the chat window, not in speech bubbles.</content></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="Interacting with Player-Characters">
<Contents><content type="text">By default, the Chat Window will show you everything said to you, and in your vicinity. You can type directly into the 'Main' tab to TALK to people quite nearby, use the /shout command to yell something to all players in range and use the /tell command (syntax: /tell FirstName Message) to talk to only one player in particular.

To issue a command, begin with the '/' character. Remember that Main chat is used for all IC dialogue and that OOC comments or questions should be kept in square brackets or parentheses in Main chat, limited to Whisper and Group chat, or sent in a /tell.

For example:

Type 'Hello!' in Main chat - You say "Hello" to the people nearby.

If you type '/shout Hi' - You shout "Hi" to everyone in the city or region.

If a character called Eliandrus says "Hi!", everyone will see: 'Eliandrus says: Hi!'

To find out which players are online; type /who

An additional command can help you to express certain actions you want to perform: /me action - You perform an action seen by people in your vicinity.

If you type '/me waves' Then everyone else will see 'Eliandrus waves'.

Just as you may TRADE with NPC merchants, player-characters may also give and/or receive items. Right-click on a player-character and choose the 'TRADE' icon to open an exchange window with two sets of inventory slots. To trade, click on the items or Tria in your Inventory and move them to the left-hand (give) slots. As you are doing this, the other player will be doing the same. You will see the items and Tria they are offering you appear in the right-hand (receive) slots. When you are happy with the trade, click 'Accept' and the items and Tria will be transferred.</content></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="Menus and Windows">
<Contents><content type="text">At the top of the screen you have a 'toolbar' with a series of 16 icons you can use to access various functions of the game. You can the icon order and layout by right-clicking on the blue crystal in the corner of the game window. (Mac users should ctrl-click or 2-finger click on the crystal to change the toolbar layout.)</content><content type="pic" src="MiniUp;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
All Windows/icons can be 'active' or 'inactive'. Clicking on an icon will make it active. Clicking on it again will deactivate it.
The size of the toolbar (as with many in game windows) can be adjusted by clicking and dragging on the triangle at the bottom right of the toolbar.

1) - Communications.</content><content type="pic" src="ChatButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This will open the chat window to allow you to interact with other players and with computer controlled characters (NPCs). When it's active the chat window is already displayed on screen. The initial chat window is divided into 4 tabs out of a possible 10. The others can be displayed by changing the Chat Tabs options (Options menu->Interface-> Chat - tabs).

If you want your character to speak to other characters, just select the Main tab, click in the middle of the window, type 'Hello' and hit the enter key.
If you want to speak with an NPC, you use the NPC tab the same way.
If you need help from our staff or volunteers, use the Help tab.

2) - Buddy List.</content><content type="pic" src="BuddyButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This window is used to show a list of all of your 'buddies'. Once open you can "Add" new names to the list, "Remove" names from the list, and "Edit" names on the list this final option allows you to add notes after the name so you can store information about the player/character.

3) - Group Stats.</content><content type="pic" src="GroupButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
When you create a group, or are invited into a group you can use this window to see names and races of all the people in the group. It will also show you the mana, and HP levels for each group member.

4) - Guild</content><content type="pic" src="GuildButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This window is where you will be able to see all the details concerning your guild, assuming you have joined one.

5) - Skills and Stats.</content><content type="pic" src="SkillsButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
Here you can find detailed lists of all of the traits for your character. These include HP (Health Points), Mana (Magic Points), your values for agility, strength, and other stats, and all the levels for all your skills you have built up. Open the skill window to review your skills, then close it by clicking on the small red 'x' on the top right of the skill window.

6) - Inventory.</content><content type="pic" src="InventoryButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This window lets you see all the objects you own, hold, wear, and carry. At the moment you don't have many, but you will by the time you finish the tutorial.

With the window open, you can EQUIP objects by clicking on them from the inventory slots and dropping them in the appropriate slots surrounding your avatar.

You can EAT food by clicking on it from your inventory and dropping it on your avatar.

The money (Tria) you own is displayed in the same window, on the right, where the coin icons are. There are four different types of coins and you should already have some of them to get you started. Be sure to check your inventory often. The NPCs in the tutorial will give you items.

7) - Quests.</content><content type="pic" src="QuestButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This window shows you completed and uncompleted (active) quests. When you click on a quest in the description window you will see auto generated Quest Notes which can help you if you get stuck with a quest.

8) - Spell Book.</content><content type="pic" src="MagicButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This window is where you can see all your collected glyphs, and all the spells you have learned. The active spells window shows all 'buffs' and 'debuffs' which are currently active on your character. Research magic lets you purify glyphs by picking one up and dropping it on the purify button.
Once the glyphs are purified, putting them in the assemble slot(s) and clicking 'Research' will let you find spells.

9) - Attack Book.</content><content type="pic" src="AttackButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This window is where you will be able to see a list of all the special attack you have learned. There are none currently released so for now there is nothing you will use this window for.

10) - Shortcut list.</content><content type="pic" src="ShortcutButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
The shortcut window allows you to create any combination of short cut you can think of. For details of the commands you can use in short cuts you should look at the "Commands" section.

11) - Information.</content><content type="pic" src="SkillsButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This opens a small window which shows compact player data. Your HP and Mana, your target's HP, a selection of attacking stances, and a sliding bar to choose 'spell power' when you use magic. It also has a series of small boxes which will be your special attack que once special attacks have been released.

12) - Active Effect Bar.</content><content type="pic" src="HotBarButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This small window shows all the effects currently active on you. Any spells, magic items, potions, curses, diseases will all be shown here. Any of them that have a timed duration will have a progress bar behind the icon. 

13) - Options.</content><content type="pic" src="OptionsButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This opens up the Options window which will let you see, set, and change all the game options. For details on all these options navigate to 'User interface' and then 'Options window' within the In-Game Help for a much more detailed explanation.

14) - Petition window.</content><content type="pic" src="PetitionButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
If you require help from a Game Master (GM) and you cannot find any online, or if you have bugs to report to the developers then you can make a new petition and essentially leave a message. A GM will either respond to the message and that will be shown in the same window, or will contact you directly in game. Different problems require the player to be online which is why you might get a slower response.

15) - Help.</content><content type="pic" src="HelpButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This opens up the Help window.

16) - Exit.</content><content type="pic" src="QuitButton_over;" padding="130" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This will open an option box asking if you want to exit the game.

</content></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="Trading with NPCs">
<Contents><content type="text">There are three main ways to GIVE ITEMS to NPCs.

First; when you give an item to an NPC in a quest. To do this you open the quest window by right-clicking on an NPC and clicking the 'TALK/LIPS' icon. If you have an option to give an NPC an item it will appear here, like all quest options. When you click this quest option you will automatically give the item to the NPC.

Second; this is another option during quests. If you try to give an item to an NPC by clicking a quest option (above) and it does not work, you can click on the "give items to npcs" button to open a trade window you can use to manually give items. You will need to move an item from your inventory into one of the give item slots, then once you have selected all the items you want to give you can click the 'ACCEPT TRADE' button. This option will likely be used if you try to use the menu option above, but it does not work. An example of this would be if you have a stack of 4 apples, but need to give an NPC 2. The server cannot take 2 items from a stack of 4 and give them to the NPC for you. So you would have to take 2 items and give them to the NPC manually using this method.

Third; is manually via the 'GIVE' option which you can find by right-clicking an NPC. If you need to give an item to an NPC in a quest, instead of using the options above you can close the quest window and right-click and NPC and choose 'GIVE' which will open a trade window just like the second option. You can then move the item(s) you want to give to the NPC into that window and click 'ACCEPT TRADE' to give that item to the NPC. 

This is the GIVE button;</content><content type="pic" src="ButtonGive;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">

There are many NPC merchants in the game. To TRADE with an NPC, right-click on the character and choose the 'BUY/SELL' icon. You can then browse the items they will buy from you and the items you can buy from them. Not every merchant will buy or sell every item, so you should search around to find the merchant you need.</content></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="Containers">
<Contents><content type="text">Containers and crafting containers come in all sorts of shapes and sizes to suit various purposes: sacks, crates and glyph bags for your possessions; furnaces and quench tanks for smithing; ovens, stoves, pots, etc. for cooking and baking; alembics, decanters, athanors, etc. for alchemy; and so on. Once you get close enough to a crafting container, right-click anywhere on it. Four icons will appear, of which 'combine' and 'use' are options you will frequently use if you learn to craft. 'Use' will only appear on containers which you need to click the 'use' button to use, if they work automatically then then use button will not be visible. The option you need to choose first is 'EXAMINE'.

This is the EXAMINE button;</content><content type="pic" src="ButtonLook;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">

When you click 'EXAMINE' the container window will open. To place items in the container you will need to move them from your inventory window into the container window. There are two ways to do this, 1 - click the 'Open Inventory' button or, 2 - click the 'Inventory' button in the toolbar. Then you need to find the item you want to move, click it once to pick it up, then move it to the container and click again to drop it in an empty slot.

After you have used the container (click 'COMBINE' or 'USE', depending on the container and what you are making), you can then move all the items back into your inventory by either clicking the 'TAKE AND STACK ALL' button, the 'TAKE ALL' button, or by picking up and moving the item into an open slot in an inventory window.
This is the TAKE ALL, and TAKE AND STACK ALL button;</content><content type="pic" src="ButtonPickup;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="Quests">
<Contents><content type="text">To access the quest window click the icon in the top toolbar called 'Quests'.

To know how to start quests read the "Interacting with NPCs" section.

Quests are of vital importance for progression in the PlaneShift world. You may begin a quest by talking to an NPC. Not all NPCs will have quests for you, however, and some may only be undertaken in sequence, after a prerequisite quest, for instance.

Quests may require you to find certain items, bring information from one place to another, fight or speak to many different NPCs. The reward for quest completion is always some *experience* and possibly money or items. Gaining experience makes your character progress and allows him to learn new skills.

Some quests you can give up on -- these are ones which you are able to repeat. To discard a quest click on the quest and then click the discard button.

You can see the status of the quests you have started and the ones you have completed by looking in the 'quest window'. The quest window is divided in 3 main sections. The top left area of the quest window displays all of your quests. You can use the 'Uncompleted' and 'Completed' buttons to show only your uncompleted and completed quests respectively. If you click on a quest, you will see the full description of that quest appear in the top right area. As you move deeper into quests this section will also display 'Automatic Quest Notes' which are pre-generated to help you keep track of where you are in a quest.

In addition, you are free to record your own notes on each quest. To do this, select the quest you want to make some notes for, then enter some text in the 'notes' section at the bottom of the window and press Save to save it. These can be useful if you want to keep detailed notes about quest(s) yourself. Please remember notes are saved locally on YOUR computer, see the "File Locations" section of In-Game Help to find the file if you want to make a backup copy.</content></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="Health and Combat Styles">
<Contents><content type="text">To check your health or the health of your opponent you should enable the 'Information' window, by clicking its icon in the top toolbar. The name and health of the creature you have selected will appear at top of this window. Your health is the largest red bar in the lower part of the window. When you have 0.00% health, you die.

When attacking an opponent you have many different options. In the window there are 6 buttons which make up the 6 different 'stances'. Those determine the level of aggression you use in combat.

The rightmost is the most aggressive, this means that you will attack without caring about defence. Use this one only when the opponent you are facing is weaker than you, or it's already injured. The leftmost button is the 'stop attack' button for when you have had enough and want to stop fighting. BE CAREFUL, this does not stop a creature from continuing to fight you. The button next to this is the most defensive stance, your attack style will be completely focused on avoiding incoming melee hits; it will lower the ability to attack a lot. If you are in danger, running away is always a possible option! Be sure to attack bigger monsters with other friends to make it easier and share the spoils.

This is the Stop Attack button.</content><content type="pic" src="ButtonStopAttack;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This is the Full Defensive Attack button.</content><content type="pic" src="ButtonAttackFullDef;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This is the Defensive Attack button.</content><content type="pic" src="ButtonAttackDefensive;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This is the Attack Normal button.</content><content type="pic" src="ButtonAttackNormal;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This is the Attack Aggressively button.</content><content type="pic" src="ButtonAttackAggressive;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
This is the Bloody Attack button.</content><content type="pic" src="ButtonAttackBloody;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="Stats and Skills">
<Contents><content type="text">To see your stats and skills click on the "SKILLS" icon on the top toolbar. Here you can see your health and mana (casting energy), along with two stamina indicators. Stamina represents how much energy you have physically and mentally. It goes down when you are performing actions like running or casting spells and it recovers automatically.
   
Strength (STR): Measures the muscular power of your body. It's useful when increased as it helps to increase damage dealt in combat, to lift heavy objects, and to break things.

Endurance (END): Expresses the general health of your body. Controls resistance to cold, heat and illness. Affects the speed of regeneration of wounds.
Agility (AGI): This represents your ability to control your body movement: it's a mix of balance and precision. It's used to perform complex tasks such as climbing walls, walking on ropes, dodging and landing hits in combat, etc.

Intelligence (INT): Indicates how quickly you can solve a riddle, make complex calculations and make logical connections between your past experience and the current situation to find a solution. It's used in casting spells of the Blue and Brown Ways.

Will (WIL): Will expresses your skill on all non-rational mental abilities like intuition and wisdom. This also represents your determination in completing tasks and reaching your goals. It's used in casting spells of the Azure and Red Ways.

Charisma (CHA): Represents the ability to convince an audience of your ideas, to lead your soldiers in battle or to attract followers. It's used in casting spells of the Crystal and Dark Ways.

In the same window you can find the knowledge you have in the various skills, like magic, sword, metallurgy, etc.</content></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="Skills Training">
<Contents><content type="text">Training can be divided between "stats" and "skills".

Training a skill is very simple. All you need to do is perform an action which gives you practice for the skill you want to train. Three examples of this are;
Casting a spell to practice magic.
Mining ores and gems to practice mining.
Fighting a creature while using a sword to train sword.

If you open your 'Stats and Skill' window you will see a bar with two colours. 'Red' is the total amount of practice you need to complete a level of training, and 'Green' which is the progress you have made to your next level. When the Red bar is filled by the Green bar then you have completed the amount of practice needed and your level is raised by 1 rank.

Training stats it is a little different. There are a total of six stats; Intelligence, Will, Charisma, Endurance, Strength, or Agility. Each of these is trained in the same way. You find an NPC which can train you in the stat you want to raise and you spend a combination of experience (which in PlaneShift is call Progression Points) and tria.

If you look in the 'Stats and Skill' window you will see the bars are different. The 'Yellow' bar indicates the amount of experience which you will need to spend on the next level, while the thin 'Blue' bar indicates how many practice points you have. When you have enough to buy the next level the blue bar will be the same length as the Yellow. At this point all you then need is enough tria to pay the trainer.

Experience (and Practice points, 1 Practice Point is 200 experience) is gained by doing exactly the same actions you perform to train a skill. As you are mining or fighting or casting magic, or performing any action you earn experience each time you complete the action.</content></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="Magic, Glyphs and Spells">
<Contents><content type="text">Magic in PlaneShift is divided into six different Ways. To find and cast spells there are three things you need to do.

First, you need to obtain and purify glyphs. A small number of glyphs can be purchased from NPCs, many players sell the more common glyphs, and the best way to get glyphs is to do quests where they are given out as rewards. To purify a glyph you need to open the 'SPELL BOOK' from the main toolbar. Then click on the icon in the bottom right-hand corner of the window, 'RESEARCH MAGIC', to open the glyph window. In this window all the glyphs are divided by Way and you will be able to purify glyphs and research spells.

Research Magic window Button.</content><content type="pic" src="Glyph Magic;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
To purify a glyph you need to left-click a glyph to pick it up and then drop it onto the 'PURIFY' Icon in the bottom left of the window. You can purify as many glyphs as you want as quickly as you can move them. If you give a glyph to another player, drop it, or give it to an NPC, you will have to re-purify it before you can use it again.

Purify Glyph Button.</content><content type="pic" src="PurifyGlyphButton;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
Second, to discover spells you need to research them. To do this you need to place one or more purified glyph(s) into the 'ASSEMBLE SLOTS'. Once you have placed one or more glyphs into the slots, starting with the one on the far left, you need to click on 'RESEARCH BUTTON'. When using two, three, or four glyphs, the order of the glyphs is important so try different orders as well as different glyphs. If you succeed you will see a new spell appear in the SPELL BOOK, if you 'fail' this will hurt your character and you will lose some HP and Mana, but don't worry, YOU CANNOT die from failing research so you can click as many times as you want.

Research Spell Button.</content><content type="pic" src="ResearchSpellButton;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
Third, you need to cast the spell. To do this you can go to the SPELL BOOK window, which lists the name of the spells and the glyphs used to cast them. You need to select the spell you want to cast by left- clicking the name, which will show an icon for the spell and a description for it. If the spell can be cast on yourself then you can immediately cast it by clicking the 'CAST' button. If it is an attack spell then you need to select the target of the spell, and then click 'CAST' to cast it.

Cast Spell Button.</content><content type="pic" src="Cast Magic;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="More Tips: Getting Help">
<Contents><content type="text">Besides the Welcome Area and In-Game Help, we have a great group of players and GMs (Game Masters) ready to help you whenever you have difficulties.

First of all look at the chat window. If you write /help [question] and then press enter, the players or GMs playing in game may be able to answer your questions. Don't be afraid to use it! Players volunteer for it so please be as clear as possible and wait patiently for an answer.

Another tool you have at your disposal is directly contacting the Game Masters. You can see if any of them are on-line by writing ' /who game master ' in the same chat window and pressing enter. You will get a list of Game Masters online in the 'system tab' and you will be able to contact them by writing /tell [name of the Game Master] [your question] and pressing enter again.

The last tool you might find useful is called petitions. It's a way to leave offline messages for the Game Masters which then they will be able to review and answer back to you later. To use this click on the appropriate icon in the toolbar (TIP: you can leave the mouse over an icon in order to see what it does) and click new. Then you will be able to write a message for Game Masters. As soon as one sees it he will claim it and you will see the name of the GM handling your petition appear in the Petition window. When they have had the time to find an answer to your question, the status of your petition will change to closed and by clicking on the petition you will be able to read the Game Master's answer.</content></Contents>
</topic>
<topic name="More Tips: Reporting Bugs">
<Contents><content type="text">PlaneShift is still a game under heavy development by a group of volunteers. Because of these there are likely many small (or big) bugs you will come across. If you want to help the developers improve the game then please take advantage of our bug tracker at;

http://www.hydlaaplaza.com/flyspray/

Anything from mistakes with crafting, to spelling mistakes in an item description or the tiniest grammar mistakes in quests are very welcomed to be reported in the bug tracker. The best way to make this game as great as possible is with the help of players. 

We thank you in advance for taking the time to report any bugs you do come across.</content></Contents>
</topic>
</branch>
<topic name="ROLEPLAY">
<Contents><content type="text">If you want to have a good experience inside our virtual world, it's important that you grasp the concepts behind roleplay. Here are the basics to start with. For a more detailed discussion, see the Roleplay section in the Player Guide.

The beauty of a virtual world is similar to the beauty of a book, where you imagine the places that are described and, during the time you read it, you identify with certain characters, react to others, participate in the story -- you become immersed in the descriptions and in the plot. But a virtual world can be even more immersive than a book. In PlaneShift you can create a new character, have him participate in the virtual world, and have the world interact back. You are asked to think about his personality and goals, and then to act them out, like if you were on a stage performing in a theatre. What's of critical importance is that the character you create in game should NOT be yourself. He is another being with his own wills, life aims, friends, fears and joys.

The difference between what your character knows and feels (in character or IC) and what YOU know and feel (out of character or OOC) is called IC/OOC SEPARATION. You have to keep this separation as strong as possible in order to increase the depth and enjoyment of roleplay. The more you are able to make it real for yourself and for others, the more you are achieving the purposes of roleplay. If you start looking at the PlaneShift world this way, things will be a lot more enjoyable, and there will be a lot more to do than just hunting monsters or getting rich in game.

You may be interested in what's allowed and what's not in terms of behaviour and speech for a good roleplay. The answer is very simple: everything that your character would do is allowed, with his knowledge, his intelligence, his attitudes. He could make friends, or enemies. He could have a job, or be a lazy lout. He should have strengths, as well as weaknesses, and hobbies, interests, quirks, habits of speech. He (the character) could be likeable, or rude, but YOU (the player) should always strive to be a considerate player.

When you have your character speak, think of what he knows, not what YOU know. Don't be afraid to approach strangers in game in character for help or just to greet someone and start an IC conversation. The main language of Yliakum is Common, which is like our modern English, minus slang and texting abbreviations. In addition, characters may know their racial languages to a greater or lesser degree. Type all in-character dialogue in the chat tab 'Main'. OOC comments or questions should be kept within square brackets or parentheses in 'Main', limited to the 'Whisper' and 'Group' tabs, or sent in the form of /tell FirstName Message.

Every character should have a distinctive appearance. Don't be afraid to start with a simple CHARACTER DESCRIPTION. You are free to modify it or add or change details any time. Right-click on your character and click on the 'EXAMINE/EYE' icon to open the 'Details' window. Click on the 'Desc' tab followed by the 'MODIFY DESCRIPTION/SCROLL' icon to write or edit your character description. Remember to include only what another character can detect using their senses. Your character's backstory or history should not appear here.</content></Contents>
</topic>
<branch name="User Interface">
<Contents><content type="text">Here you will find descriptions of PlaneShift windows.</content></Contents>
<topic name="Active Effects">
<Contents><content type="text">The active effect window shows all the active effects you have. There are lots of settings for this window which can be changed in the options window.

You can show all effects from items, or items and all 'timed effects' such as spells, curses, poisons, diseases, and indigestion.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Attack Book">
<Contents><content type="text">There are currently no special attacks released so this window has no current use.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Buddy List window">
<Contents><content type="text">This window allows you to manage your PlaneShift friends list and can be opened and closed by clicking on the 'Interlocked Rings' icon of your toolbar. With the "Add" button you can add new characters to your buddy list. The "Remove" button allows you to remove the currently selected character from your buddy list.

When the character is in game, his or her name changes from red (offline) to green. By clicking on a green character name, you can send that character a /tell (for example /tell Smith hello, how are you?).

With the "Edit" button you can rename an entry in the buddy list. This can be used for example to add information about which guild that character belongs too. These aliases are not saved on the server but your own computer so they won't be available if you login from a different computer.
Additional Info: All names on your buddy list are available for the tab-completion function in your chat box, meaning that if you type the first few letters of any name on your buddy list and hit the 'tab' key, the whole name will be automatically written into your chat box. (See Chat window->Tab Completion for more.)
Icon for the Buddy List window.</content><content type="pic" src="BuddyButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents></topic>
<branch name="Chat window"><Contents><content type="text">The chat window is opened and closed by clicking on the 'Speech Bubble' icon in your toolbar. This is probably the most important window in PlaneShift, because it enables most of the interaction between players. Commands can be executed by typing them in this window.

To configure which tabs are shown (out of a total of 10), go to Options->Interface->Chat - Tabs. You can also configure which messages are sent in the Main tab. The currently selected chat tab is highlighted, and a tab will "flash" when a new, unread message arrives.</content><content type="pic" src="ChatButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents>
            <topic name="Configuring Chat Tabs"><Contents><content type="text">There are a total of 10 different chat tabs.

To configure which tabs are shown, go to Options->Interface->Chat - Tabs. You can also configure which messages are sent in the Main tab. For example, you could have 'Main', 'System' and 'Auction' all show in the main chat tab if you wanted.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Tab-Completion"><Contents><content type="text">The chat window supports a tab-completion function for names, commands, and some words. To make use of this, just start writing the first letters of a name, command, or specified word then press the tab-key on your keyboard. In case there is more than one possible word that could be completed, all of them will be written to the system chat tab. You can specify in the in-game options any additional words you want to include in tab-completion. All names on your buddy list, names of characters that said something in chat, and all chat commands are automatically included in the tab-completion function. The function applies to all chat tabs.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Spellchecker"><Contents><content type="text">On Linux and MacOSX there is a basic spellcheck function for the chat window that can be enabled or disabled in the in-game Options (Options->Interface-Advanced->Chat-Spellchecker). There is no default dictionary, but Information about installing a dictionary for the spellchecker is found in the same window (Options->Interface-Advanced->Chat-Spellchecker).</content></Contents></topic>
<branch name="Chat Tabs"><Contents><content type="text">Descriptions of the chat tabs and their uses.</content></Contents>
<topic name="Main"><Contents><content type="text">As the name implies, this is the main chat tab, intended for interaction between characters. Everything typed here has a limited saying-range and only people within that range can see what you typed. This tab is In-Character (IC), meaning that this is the voice of your character, not you. Your character has no clue about what music you listen to at the moment or even that PlaneShift is just a game. For short Out-of-character (OOC) announcements like "afk" please use brackets: "[afk]" or "[brb, phone]". You can filter the information displayed in this tab by going to Options->Interface->Chat Tabs and checking/unchecking the "Main Tab" options.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Chat/Channels"><Contents><content type="text">This chat tab is used primarily for the "Gossip" channel, which is meant for Out-of-character chatting. This chat tab has no range limit and people all over the server can see your message.

You can also join and leave additional channels using the commands "/join" and "/leave". For example "/join gossip". Once you have joined a new channel, the server will assign a number to it. By default gossip is '1' the next channel you join will be '2' then '3' etc... To leave a channel you need to use that number and not the channel name for example "/leave 1"

If you are only in one channel, any text you type will automatically be sent to the channel upon pressing return. If you are in more than one channel, you have to start your line with /1 or /2 or /3 etc... this is the same number that you were given when you created/joined the channel and is the same number you have to use when you leave that channel.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="NPC"><Contents><content type="text">This chat tab is for interaction with NPCs (Non-Player-Characters). Though most quests are done with the chat-bubble interface, it's still possible to communicate with NPCs by writing in this chat tab. This tab also allows you to refer to what an NPC told you during a quest in your current play session. Other players cannot see what you type in this tab. You need to have a NPC selected to talk to them.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Whisper"><Contents><content type="text">This tab is for private one-to-one communication. Whatever you type in this tab will be seen only by the player you send a tell to. There is no range limit -- you can talk to any player on the server. Normally all chat in this tab is OOC but it's accepted to roleplay whispering to other characters with this tab after making clear in the Main chat that your character whispers to another (What is visible for all people nearby).

Be careful when using this tab: Your messages will always be sent to the last person who sent a tell to you, unless you specify the intended recipient. So if you are in a /tell conversation and you get a tell from another person just before completing your current tell and pressing enter, most likely the wrong person (the new person) will get your message. To prevent this you can always send your tells with "/tell CHARNAME" or by pressing the f-key which will start a tell to the person who just sent you one.

You can also double click a name in your buddy list which will open a message box you can use to send messages to one character.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Guild"><Contents><content type="text">If you are in a guild you can use this chat tab to communicate with your guild mates. Whether Guild chat is In-Character or Out-of-Character seems to be a matter of the rules adopted by that guild -- check with the guild leader and guild mates. There is no range limit and all people in your guild can read your messages. If you don't see this tab, enable it from Options->Interface->Chat Tabs</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Group"><Contents><content type="text">This chat tab is for chatting with people in your current group. You may create a group and invite a player to join it by typing the command /invite [Char-name]. Any member can leave the group but only the group's creator may disband it. There is no range limit -- you can talk to everyone in the same group as you anywhere on the server. Whether Group chat is In-Character or Out-of-Character depends on the rules adopted by the group. Group chat can have many uses, for example, to roleplay In-Character in a closed room when nobody outside should be able to hear what is said; or to communicate OOCly to enhance coordination in a roleplay.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Alliance"><Contents><content type="text">If you are in a guild and your guild is part of an alliance you can use this chat tab to talk to all allies. Whether Alliance chat is In-Character or Out-of-Character depends on the rules adopted by the alliance -- check with the alliance leader and alliance members.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Auction"><Contents><content type="text">This chat tab is used for selling and buying goods. This is an In-Character chat tab (enforced) so please avoid Out-of-Character text here or if really needed mark it with [brackets]. No character has a clue about weapon statistics and qualities so if you absolutely need them put them in [brackets] as well. The Range limit of the Auction tab is about the same as the /shout range of the Main tab.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="System"><Contents><content type="text">The system tab is for system messages like combat damage, crafting progress or the output of some chat commands like /who. Through the Options menu (Options->Interface->Chat-Tabs) you can redirect these messages to Main tab if you like. You can also select which combat messages about yourself or others appear in your system messages (Options->Interface-Advanced->Chat-Filters).</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Help"><Contents><content type="text">The Help chat tab is where you can get help if you are having issues with the game. Everything you type here will be visible to online advisors and GMs. Remember: advisors may be other players, and may not have GM powers. Once an advisor answers, everything you type in the chat is only visible for you and that advisor until the help-session times out. This chat tab is for questions about the game mechanics and how to play the game. No advisor is allowed to give out spoilers like where to find a specific trainer or how to solve a quest. For further information about becoming an advisor yourself, check the documentation of the /advisor chat command.</content></Contents></topic></branch></branch>
<topic name="Group Stats window"><Contents><content type="text">The names and a representative image of the characters in your current group are shown in this window. Note that the health and mana bars for these characters may not accurately reflect their actual statistics, especially if they are located far away.

Group leaders can invite or dismiss people or disband the whole group by right-clicking the window. The group leader is always shown as the topmost character in the list. If this player logs out, the next one in the list will become group leader.</content><content type="pic" src="GroupButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents></topic>
<branch name="Guild Info window"><Contents><content type="text">If your character is in a guild, this window allows you to change basic information about the guild. You may need the appropriate permissions in order to use or change some functions. The buttons at the top allow you access to other tabs with more specific information about the guild.</content><content type="pic" src="GuildButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents>
<topic name="Settings"><Contents><content type="text">The "Guild message of the day" is visible to every guild member from this window. With the "Refresh MOTD" Button you can reload the current message in case someone else in your guild changed it while you had the Guild window open. "Save MOTD" allows you to save your changes to the message and makes them visible for everyone else in the guild.
With the "Change" button next to the guild's name, you can rename the guild.

By checking the "Secret Guild" option, the guild will become secret. This means that only guild members will be able to see the guild tags above characters and the name of the guild won't be displayed next to the character name when someone types /who.

With the "Change" button next to the website address,  you can change the guild's URL.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Members"><Contents><content type="text">This is the member list of the guild, displaying the name, details and location of each guild member.

With the "Online only" option you can filter the list to show only characters that are currently in game.
The "Invite" button allows you to invite new characters to the guild.
The "Leave" button allows you to leave the guild.
If the "Notify when members login/logout" option is enabled, you will get a message in the Guild chat tab each time a member logs in or out.
The "Remove" button allows you to remove the currently selected member from the guild.
The "Edit level" button allows you to change the guild level of the currently selected member. You can only change/set a new level which is at least one level below your own guild level.
The "Edit points" button allows you to edit the guild points of the selected member.
The "Public notes" button allows you to edit the public notes for the selected member.
The "Private notes" button allows you to edit the private notes for the selected member.
The "Edit Max GP" button allows you to change the maximum amount of guild points each character can achieve.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Permissions"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can change the permissions allowed for different guild levels as well as change the names of the guild levels. To change the name just click on the guild level at the left and give it a new name.
Permissions:

- View Chat: If this is enabled, members of this guild level can read the guild chat.
- Chat: If this is enabled, members of this guild level can write in the guild chat.
- Invite: If this is enabled, members of this guild level can invite new characters to the guild.
- Remove: If this is enabled, members of this guild level can remove characters from the guild. But they can only remove characters with a lower guild level than their own.
- Promote: If this is enabled, members of this level can promote or demote other characters. They can only change the level of members with a lower level than themselves and only promote them to at least one level lower than themselves.
- Privileges: If this is enabled, members of this guild level can edit the permissions for all guild levels lower than their own.
- Points: If this is enabled, members of this level can edit the guild points of all characters with a lower guild level than their own.
- Edit: If this is enabled, members of this guild level can edit the general information of the guild like the MOTD or the name of the guild.
- Pub notes / Public notes: If this is enabled, members of this level can edit the public notes of other characters.
- Prv notes / Private notes: If this is enabled, members of this level can edit the private notes of other characters.
- -w al.Chat / View Alliance chat: If this is enabled, members of this level can read the alliance chat.
- All.Chat / Alliance Chat: If this is enabled, members of this level can write in the alliance chat.
- Guild Bank: If this is enabled, members of this level have access to the guild banking account at a banking NPC.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Alliance"><Contents><content type="text">If your guild is part of an alliance, here you can see and manage alliance information.

- Invite: Allows the alliance leader to invite more guilds to the alliance.
- Disband: Allows the alliance leader to dissolve the alliance.
- Leave: Allows the guild leader to withdraw their guild from the alliance.
- Remove: Allows the alliance leader to remove a guild from the alliance.
- Make leader: Allows the alliance leader to transfer leadership to another guild's leader.
If the "Notify when alliance members login/logout" option is enabled, you get a message in Alliance chat each time a member of one of the member guilds logs in or out.
With the "Create alliance" button a guild leader can create a new alliance.
The following information is displayed in the table of member guilds of the alliance:
Name (Name of the guild which is part of the alliance)
Status (The status of the guild i.e. whether alliance leader or not)
Leader (The name of the leader of this guild)
Online (Whether the leader of the guild is online at the moment)</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<topic name="Help window"><Contents><content type="text">This window displays the In-Game Help.</content><content type="pic" src="HelpButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Information window"><Contents><content type="text">The info window gives you an overview of combat and casting options and several key statistics relevant to your character and your current target, especially in combat situations. When a target is selected, the window displays the character or object name and below it a large red bar showing the current health of the target.

The next line is the current time in Yliakum.

Below the time are several icons for the different stances you can take during combat. Stances represent the combat style of your character in melee. If you are in combat you can click on any of the icons to change to that stance. The first icon stops the attack. Stances from left to right: Fully Defensive, Defensive, Normal, Aggressive, and Bloody.

Below the stances is a slider that allows you to specify how much power you want to channel into casting magic. The more power you channel, the greater the likelihood of the spell failing, but if successful the spell effect will be stronger and its duration longer.
Below the slider are another 4 bars. The larger red one displays the current health of your character, the smaller red one your current physical stamina. The larger blue bar shows your current mana, the smaller blue one your current mental stamina.</content><content type="pic" src="InfoButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Inventory window"><Contents><content type="text">The Inventory window allows you to manage the belongings of your character and to use, equip, and unequip items.

Surrounding the image of your avatar are equipment slots that hold specific kinds of items. Move your cursor over each slot to find out what it holds. To equip an item or change equipped items, drag them from or to your inventory slot. A system message will alert you if you are trying to equip an item that will not fit.

Hand; Left, and Right: For equipping tools, shields, weapons and all other hand-held items. Please note many crafting techniques require you to hold the tool in your right hand. For roleplay purposes, many items such as food, books or ore may be held.
Helm: For caps and helms.
Mind: This is for equipping crafting books. You need to have the book for your current crafting task equipped in this slot to be able to perform the task.
Right, Left Finger: For rings.
Neck: For necklaces and amulets.
Gloves: For gloves.
Torso: For torso armor.
Bracers: For bracers.
Back: For robes.
Arms: For arms armor.
Boots: For boots.
Legs: For pants.
Belt: For belts.

Below the equipment area are 24 inventory slots for items your character is carrying. Each stack of item needs one inventory slot. You can stack up to 65 items in one slot, but not all items can be stacked - books or containers for example. Your inventory space can be extended by carrying containers (for example a chest or a pouch). If you right-click a container a new window with a few more slots will show up. Each container also has a limited capacity.

On the right hand side of the Infomation window, beside your avatar image, you can see how much weight you carry at the moment and the maximum weight you can carry, as well as your current and maximum capacity. (Capacity represents the space taken up by each item, as items have size values in addition to their weight.) You can also see how much money you are currently carrying, and how many of each of the four coin types you have.

To have your character drop an item, click to pick it up from the inventory and move the icon to where you want to drop it in the 3D environment. To decide on a place you can left-click once. Once this is done, you enter 'edit mode' where you can rotate the object to change its angle before it is finally placed. To do this, hold right- click and move the mouse. You can also hold shift and move the mouse to change the axis the item is rotated around. To finally place the item left-click again.

To eat or use a items like potions, food, herbal and alchemical items, drag/pick them up and release/left-click on the image of your avatar..
There are shortcut keys for taking one item of a stack or taking the whole stack. If you click on a stack of items while holding the shift-key, only one of the items is taken. If you hold the ctrl-key the whole stack is taken. If you left-click on a stack, you will be prompted to specify how many of that item you wish to take.</content><content type="pic" src="InventoryButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents></topic>
<branch name="Options window"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can change or select game options. In general the options are changed only when you click "Save". The "Reset" button will set everything back to the defaults. If you don't want to change any existing options but also don't want to go back to the defaults, just click on the 'x' icon to close the window.</content><content type="pic" src="OptionsButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents>
<topic name="Controls/Keys"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can change the keys (and mouse buttons) used to play the game. To assign a new key or button to an action, just use the "Set" button next to the action.

Movements:
"MouseMove" - Move your character to the position your mouse currently points to.
"Forward" - Makes your character move forward (available two times to be able to set up two alternative keys for this)
"Backward" - Makes your character move backward (available two times to be able to set up two alternative keys for this)
"Rotate left" - Makes your character rotate to the left (available two times to be able to set up two alternative keys for this)
"Rotate right" - Makes your character rotate to the right (available two times to be able to set up two alternative keys for this)
"Strafe right" - Makes your character step to the right (available two times to be able to set up two alternative keys for this)
"Strafe left" - Makes your character step to the left (available two times to be able to set up two alternative keys for this)

Modifiers:
"Run" - Depending on your current movement default, pressing this key makes your character either run or walk. If your character runs without this key, holding it down while moving will make your character walk.
"ToggleRun" - Changes your default moving behaviour between run and walk.
"AutoMove" - Will make your character walk forward until the key is pressed again.
"Sneak" - As long as this key is held down your character will sneak.

Actions:
"Jump" - Makes your character jump.
"Sit" - This will toggle between your character sitting down and standing up again.

Camera:
"Camera mode" - Cycles between the different camera modes available in PlaneShift.
"Look up" - Makes the camera look up.
"Look down" - Makes the camera look down.
"Zoom in" - Makes the camera zoom in on your character.
"Zoom out" - Makes the camera zoom out from your character.
"Center camera" - Makes the camera move back to its default position. Makes sense only in some camera modes.
"MouseLook" - As long as this key is held down the camera will follow your mouse movements.
"Toggle MouseLook" - Pressed once the camera will follow all your mouse movements until the key is pressed again.
"CameraForward/Back" - While holding down this key, you can change the camera distance by moving your mouse forward and backward.

Game Controls:
"Close" - Closes active windows.
"Toggle Chat" - Activates the chat window and allows you to start typing.
"Reply tell" - Allows you to answer a tell by automatically writing /tell [Character-name] with the name of the last person to send you a tell.
"Communications" - Opens and closes the chat window.
"Options" - Opens and closes the options window.
"Spell book" - Opens and closes the spell book.
"Stats" - Opens and closes the Stats and skills window.
"Inventory" - Opens and closes the Inventory window.
"Bag" - Opens and closes a smaller version of the inventory window that doesn't allow equipping and dequipping of items. Useful during trades.
"Help" - Opens and closes the Help window.
"Buddy" - Opens and closes the Buddy list.
"Buy" - Opens and closes the trade window for the selected NPC or player.
"Quit" - Quits PlaneShift.
"Brightness up" - Increases the general brightness of the graphics in PlaneShift.
"Brightness down" - Decreases the general brightness of the graphics in PlaneShift.
"Brightness Reset" - Resets the general brightness of the graphics in PlaneShift.

Shortcuts:
Here you can reassign keys for shortcuts or name the 'Unused' slots (click 'Set' beside an 'Unused' slot) and create your own shortcuts.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Controls/Mouse"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can change some general mouse settings.

"ContextMenu" - Which mouse button brings up the context menu for game entities.
"EntitySelect" - Which mouse button selects game entities.
"EntityDragDrop" - The mouse button that allows you to drag and drop items.
"EntityDragDropOne" - The mouse button that allows you to drag and drop one item from a stack of items.
"EntityDragDropAll" - The mouse button that allows you to drag and drop a whole stack of items.
Settings:
"InvertMouse" - Inverts the up and down direction of the mouse during camera movement.
"HorzSensitivity" - The sensitivity of the mouse in horizontal direction during camera movement. A lower value means the mouse will be less sensitive.
"VertSensitivity" - The sensitivity of the mouse in vertical direction during camera movement. A lower value means the mouse will be less sensitive.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Controls/Entities"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can specify what happens for a double-click on different game entities.

"Items" - Action if an item is double-clicked.
"Players" - Action if a player is double-clicked.
"Merchants" - Action if an NPC merchant is double-clicked.
"Alive NPCs" - Action if an alive NPC is double-clicked (usually an enemy or monster).
"Dead NPCs" - Action if a dead NPC is double-clicked.
"Pet NPCs" - Action if a pet NPC is double-clicked.
"Impervious NPCs" - Action if an impervious NPC is double-clicked (usually story NPCs).</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Sound/General"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can enable specific sound sources in PlaneShift and control their volume. If you are not hearing any sounds, first check that sound is enabled in the PlaneShift Launcher (click on 'Settings' and 'Audio' in the Launcher window).

"Master Volume" - Overall volume of all enabled sounds.
"Background Music" - The theme music of each map.
"Ambient sounds" - Sounds like birds or water fountains.
"Action sounds" - Hammering at the anvil, attacking...
"Effect Sounds" - Mainly the sounds of magic spells.
"Interface Sounds" - Every sound of the PlaneShift interface, for example the "click" if you press a button.
"Voices" - NPC voices.
"Instruments" - Sounds of the music mechanics of PlaneShift.
"Sound location" - This defines if the sounds are played as if heard by your character or by your camera.
"Combat Music" - If enabled, special music will be played during combat.
"Mute on focus loss" - If enabled, PlaneShift music and other sounds are muted when the PlaneShift client window is no longer the active window on your desktop.
"Loop background music" - If enabled, the theme music automatically repeats.
"Sound on private tells" - If enabled, there is a sound notification when you receive a tell.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Graphics/Brightness"><Contents><content type="text">Please note that the screen resolution, client window size and graphic quality options are available only in the PlaneShift Launcher (click on 'Settings' and 'Graphics' in the Launcher). Use your keyboard/monitor controls to adjust the brightness of your monitor.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Graphics/Details"><Contents><content type="text">This window comes in two slightly different views depending on whether "Adaptive distance" is enabled or not.

If it's disabled, "Distance" means how far you can see in PlaneShift.

If it's enabled, "Min. distance" means the minimum distance you always want to be able to see. The closer your current frames per second rate gets to "Min. FPS" the less you will be able to see while if your frames per second rate gets closer to "Max. FPS" PlaneShift will automatically show more of the surroundings.

"FPS cap" will set a maximum for the frames per second rate PlaneShift will never exceed. There isn't usually any sense in having PlaneShift display more frames per second than the refresh rate of your monitor so setting this to a reasonable number will make PlaneShift use less resources.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Graphics/Labels"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can set which labels you want to see and what color they should be.

Labels visibility:
"Creatures" and "Items" - "Always" will always show the labels. "On Mouse" will show labels when you hover your mouse above the entity. "On Target" will show labels when you have the entity selected. And "Never" will never show the label at all.
"Show guild" - Checking the box will include the name of the guild for players in the label (Only if the guild is public. Secret guilds won't be shown this way except if you are a member of the guild).

Colours:
To change the colour of a label just click the "set" button and choose the color you want. With "Default" you can set it back to the default colour.

"Items" - All items in PlaneShift. (This does not apply to the map geometry. In some cases useable items are actually part of the map and not some dropped item. Examples are some preparation tables and furnaces. For those a label will never be shown).
"Players" - Other players.
"NPC" - All NPCs.
"Dead bodies" - recently deceased people or monsters.
"Testers" - Members of the testing team of PlaneShift.
"GM1" - The Game Master assistants.
"GM2-5" - The Game Masters.
"Developers" - For people part of the official PlaneShift team. In general they do not show up in game as visible entities.
"Grouped with you" - Player characters that are in the same group as you.
"Grouped with you and in the same guild" - Player characters who are your guild mates as well as group mates.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Graphics/Shadows"><Contents><content type="text">Check the box to enable shadows beneath characters and objects.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface/Language"><Contents><content type="text">The PlaneShift interface may be displayed in some native languages. To select yours, click 'Settings' and the 'Language' dropdown in the PlaneShift Launcher.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface/Chat-Tabs"><Contents><content type="text">The initial chat window is divided into 4 tabs out of a possible 10. The 'Main tab' column on the left allows you to filter the messages that appear in your Main chat tab, while the 'Tabs to show' column on the right allows you to separate your messages and type your dialogue into different tabs. Remember to click 'Save' after making any changes.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface/Chat-font"><Contents><content type="text">The options in this window allow you to adjust the text which appears in the 'Chat window'. You are able to adjust the font style, the size of the text, and the spacing between the words.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface/Pop-ups"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can setup the behaviour of some pop-up windows and on-screen text.

"Show Active Magic window" - Display the windows with the buffs/debuffs each time if a new magic effect affects your character.
"Show Error Messages on screen" - Display error messages on the screen (e.g. if you are out of range to use an item).
"Show Info Messages on screen" - Display information messages on the screen (e.g. if you started working on something).
"Show Result Messages on screen" - Display result messages on the screen (e.g. the outcome of your latest crafting task).
"Show OK Messages on screen" - Display confirmation that your actions have been accepted (e.g. trade completed/declined messages, NPC buy/sell messages, storage messages, etc.)
"Show ACK Messages on screen" - Display messages that acknowledge your actions (e.g. that a screenshot has been taken or a book or description saved, etc.)
"Use NPC Dialog bubbles" - Uses the "chat bubble" interface for communicating with NPCs. We strongly recommend keeping the default setting (checked/selected).
"NPC Message Timeout" - This option varies the time for which lines of text spoken by NPCs in quests are displayed.
</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface/Tooltips"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can enable or disable the tooltips (the labels that appear when you hover the cursor over toolbar icons) and customise their colors.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface/Chat-Logs"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can set up how PlaneShift logs all your messages. On the left side you can select a specific chat type and then define on the right side whether it is logged at all (select "Enable logging") and how it will be logged.

The "Log Filename" will be appended to your character name and then used as the filename to save in. Several sources can be logged in the same filename. If a "Log Bracket" is specified (e.g. [Guild]), it will be added to the start of every line of that type in the file. When re-reading chat logs, the log bracket can be useful, for example, to indicate whether a line was in Main chat or in Guild chat.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface/Shortcut Bar"><Contents><content type="text">The options here allow you to customise components of the 'Shortcut' window.

Button Height - This slider lets you choose the height of the shortcut buttons.
Button Width - This lets you manually set button width, in which case every button will be the same width. Or automatic button width, in which case the minimum width for each button will be chosen based on the button label. Labels with longer names will be much wider than those with shorter names.
Edit Lock - Prevent All Editing - This will stop you from being able to edit any shortcut in any way until you click the small 'lock icon' to unlock the shortcut bar.
Edit Lock - Prevent only Drag-n-drop - This option will let you right click a shortcut to edit the content. But if you want to move a shortcut to another position in the list you will need to click the small lock icon to unlock the option. You can then click to pick up a shortcut, and can then drop it on another shortcut to replace it. Be careful as the shortcut you drop it on will be deleted and replaced.
Scroll Buttons - These options turn on/off certain scroll bar options.
Font - Allows you to chose the font style for the button labels.
Text Size - Allows you to set the size of the font in the button labels.
Text Spacing - Allows you to set the amount of space between the text and the edges of the buttons.
Show button background - This shows/hides the button background.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface/Active Effect Bar"><Contents><content type="text">This Window allows you to customise the Active Effect Bar.

Icon display - This allows you to chose to display only effects with a duration such as spells, or both timed and permanent effects such as spell and item effects.
Button Height - This option sets the height of the active effect button.
Button Width - This lets you manually set button width, in which case every button will be the same width. Or automatic button width, in which case the minimum width for each button will be chosen based on the button label. Labels with longer names will be much wider than those with shorter names.

Warn Level - This allows you to set the point at which the effect timer changes colour as an initial warning the effect is coming to an end.
Danger Level - This allows you to set the point at which the effect timer changes colour again as a second warning level that the effect is coming to an end.
Flash Level - Allows you to chose the point at which the effect timer begins to flash. 

Use Images - This allows you to display either the image(s) or the name(s) of the item(s)/spell(s) giving an active effect.
Auto-Resize - This option give the window the ability to grow and shrink as the number of effects increases and decreases.
Show Active Effect Window - This shows/hides the window.
</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface/HP and Mana bars"><Contents><content type="text">This window controls the options for the colour changes and flashing for the HP and MANA bars in the 'information window' the 'skill window' and the 'shortcut window'.

Warn Level - This is the first warning level, when the HP or Mana reaches this level the bar will change colour.
Danger Level - This is the second warning level, when the HP or Mana reaches this level the bar will change colour for a second time.
Flash Level - This is the third and final warning level, when the HP or Mana reaches this level the bar will begin flashing.

</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Confirmations/PvP"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can set the default behaviour if another player challenges you to a duel.

"Never accept" - Reject the duel right away.
"Confirm each time"- Brings up a message box asking if the duel should be accepted or not.
"Always accept" - Accept the duel every time automatically. (Be careful using this setting! The only way to notice you are in a duel is by checking your System messages.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Confirmations/Marriage"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can set the default behaviour if another player proposes to you.

"Never accept" - Always rejects the proposal.
"Confirm each time" - Brings up a message box asking if you want to accept the proposal.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface - Advanced/Chat"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can change some general settings of the chat window as well as the color of different actions in the chat.

Colors are set by specifying the red, green and blue components of each, using a value from 0 to 255.
"Auto Tab selection" [broken] - The 'Don't autoselect' option means that the line you send will always appear in your active chat tab. The 'Select fitting Tab' option allows your chat window to switch to the appropriate tab where indicated (e.g. type /g [line] for Guild tab, /tell [character-name][line] for Whisper tab, etc.). The 'Select Main Tab' option means that your Main tab becomes active whenever you send a line that cannot be displayed in your current tab.
"Join default channel" - Joins the "gossip" channel at startup.
"Echo screen text" - If enabled, messages that are displayed on screen are also written to the chat window (usually System tab).
"Main chat brackets"  - If enabled, messages in Main chat will be prefaced by [guild], [tell], [alliance], etc. , provided you selected for other tab messages to show in Main (Interface->Chat-Tabs, left column).
"Mix your text color" - If this is selected and two or more colors apply for a chat action they get mixed.
"Lose focus on send" [broken] - If this is selected, you will automatically be able to continue with your current action e.g. continuous walking, after you hit 'Enter/Return' to send a chat line. If this is unselected, your cursor remains in the chat window after you send the line, allowing you to type another line immediately.
"Default last chat" - Automatically starts each new line with a command that will put it in the same chat tab as the previous line.
"Filter incoming bad words" - Applies the bad-words filter to all incoming chat lines from others.
"Filter outgoing bad words" - Applies the bad-words filter to all your lines before sending them.
Tip: The bad words filter can be a great tool for correcting typos. For example. You can define "teh" and have it always replaced with "the".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface - Adv/Chat-Filters"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can filter several combat messages from your chat. Selecting them allows them to appear as System messages. Messages that refer to other characters will be visible to you only if they are within range of your character.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface - Adv/Chat-Bubbles"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can set up the chat bubble behaviour and colors.
Colors are specified by defining their red, green and blue components, choosing a value from 0 to 255 for each. With "Alignment" you can specify how the text should be aligned inside the bubbles. Each chat bubble type can be enabled or disabled individually with the "Enable" checkbox next to it.

"Enable Chat Bubbles"- Enables or disables all chat bubbles.
"Max Line Length" - Defines how long a line in the chat bubble can be before wrapping to the next line.
"Short Phrase Char Count" - Defines the upper character limit in order for a phrase to qualify as a "short phrase" and be displayed in any chat bubble for shorter than the normal duration. e.g. Entering the value '10' means that any phrase less than 10 characters long qualifies as a short phrase and remains displayed in a chat bubble for a shorter time than normal.
"Long Phrase Line Count" - Defines the lower line limit in order for a phrase to qualify as a "long phrase" and be displayed in any chat bubble for longer than the normal duration. e.g. Entering the value '5' means that any message more than 5 lines long qualifies as a "long phrase" and remains displayed in a chat bubble for a longer time than normal.
"Mix Action colors" - Mix the text colors where applicable.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface - Adv/Chat-TabCompletion"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can add your own list of words for the tab completion function. Tab completion allows you to type the first letter or first few letters of a word, phrase or character name in the chat window and have the word or name completed when you press the Tab key. Each phrase you enter should be on a separate line.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface - Adv/Chat-Spellchecker"><Contents><content type="text">There is no default dictionary, but Information about installing a dictionary for the spellchecker (supported on Linux and MacOSX) is found in this window. After installing a dictionary, you can enable the spellchecker for the chat window as well as add your own words to it and set the color of typos, specifying colors by defining red, green and blue components each ranging in value from 0 to 255.
New words are added on the left side. Each word must be entered on a separate line.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface - Adv/Autoexec"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can specify commands that are executed each time you login. "Enable execution of start-up scripts" - Enables or disables the execution of these commands at a login.
The commands entered in the upper box are executed for every character you login while the ones in the lower box are executed only for your current character.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Interface - Adv/Camera"><Contents><content type="text">Here you can change several options of the different camera modes. Not all options are available for all modes but if they are available they usually have the same meaning across modes.

"Spring Length" - How long the camera continues to move after the character stops. Higher values mean the camera keeps on moving more after the character stops.
"Spring Coefficient" - The speed the camera swings when encountering an obstacle.
"Dampening Coefficient" - The speed the camera swings when encountering an obstacle.
"Min Camera Distance" - How far you can zoom the camera in.
"Max Camera Distance" - How far you can zoom the camera out.
"Camera Distance" - How far away the camera is.
"Starting pitch" - At what speed the camera starts to move.</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<topic name="Petitions window"><Contents><content type="text">This window allows you to contact GMs if no GM is currently online. Petitions are useful for reporting login problems (use another character from the same account to /petition if you are unable to login one of your characters), quest issues, requests such as the temporary locking down of ingame items for RP, and other game problems/requests.

Click "New" to create a new petition and "OK" when you are done. In the "Manage Petitions" window you will see a list of all your current petitions and their status. GMs will usually add their answer to your petition so make sure to check that your petition has been processed. Once you have the answer of the GMs and the petition is marked 'Closed', you can delete the petition. An Open petition can be modified and then saved.</content><content type="pic" src="PetitionButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Quests window"><Contents><content type="text">This window allows you to keep track of your open and completed quests as well as your current and completed GM events. When you select a quest in the list on the left-hand side, automatic quest notes appear in the 'Description' box on the right-hand side. These quest notes are automatically generated by the server as you progress through a quest, and function as a good reminder of the stages in a completed quest or where you left off in an uncompleted quest. Additional notes may be written in the 'Your notes' box and saved to your computer, not the server. (They will not be available if you login on a different computer.) Click on 'Reload' to load your last saved version of notes. (This will overwrite all changes made since your last 'Save'.)

The "Discard" button allows you to drop uncompleted repeatable quests. You will receive a System notification if you attempt to discard a quest that can be done only once and hence cannot be discarded.</content><content type="pic" src="QuestButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Quit window"><Contents><content type="text">Opens a window allowing you to confirm if you wish to exit PlaneShift.</content><content type="pic" src="QuitButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Shortcuts window"><Contents><content type="text">This window allows you to define shortcuts for frequently used actions. Default and custom shortcuts are displayed on named buttons in this window. Click to execute the shortcut.

Right-click on any button to change its assigned command/s or right-click on an empty button to create and name a new shortcut. You can create up to 200 different shortcuts. Each shortcut must have a name. Put this in first, as if you forget, your shortcut will not be saved. In the 'Enter the commands' box, enter the commands that should be executed for the shortcut. Each command must be entered on a separate line. You may enter any of the chat window commands.

The 'Clear' button will empty all fields of the shortcut.
With the 'Set' button you can assign a key to your shortcut. This can also be done in the in-game-options but is usually easier here.
Icons can be assigned to each shortcut for a cleaner display. This will replace the shortcut's name in the main window with the assigned icon. This association can be cancelled using the 'Clear Icon' button.

With 'Done' your changes will be saved while 'Cancel' will discard them.
Tips and suggestions:

Shortcuts can be created by using the 'drag and drop' feature, after unlocking the panel. This works for spells, consumables, etc.
Spoken lines should be prefaced by the /say command, but emotes require only /me followed by the action.
You can apply a given shortcut to a target. For example, creating a shortcut for /say "Good day, $target!" in the 'Enter the commands' box will have your character say in Main chat, "Good day, [targeted character or item]!". Other fields applicable besides the target's name are: $guild (target's guild), $race (target's race), $sir (target's gender).

By prefacing a line with #, you can add notes to yourself in the 'Enter the commands' box. Any line beginning with # will be skipped in processing. For example,
# long greeting
/say /me waves to everyone present.
/say "Howdy folks, looks like another fine day to be gathered for a drink! First round's on me!"
A shortcut containing the three lines above will return only the emote and dialogue to Main chat.</content><content type="pic" src="ShortcutButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/></Contents></topic>
<branch name="Spell Book window"><Contents><content type="text">The spell book lists all your currently known spells.
</content><content type="pic" src="MagicButton_over;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text"> 
You can select a spell on the left side to get more information about it, which will show on the right side.
</content><content type="pic" src="Cast Magic;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
With the 'Cast' button you can cast the currently selected spell. If the spell can be cast on yourself a target does not need to be selected. If it is an attack spell, you must have a target selected for you to be able to cast the spell.
</content><content type="pic" src="Defensive Magic;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
The 'Active Spells' button opens a window which shows all magic effects currently influencing your character. (This includes effects of magic items or Dakkru's Curse as well as spells).
</content><content type="pic" src="Glyph Magic;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/><content type="text">
The 'Research Magic' button opens the window for purifying glyphs or researching new spells.
</content></Contents>
<topic name="Research Magic">
<Contents><content type="text">You can access this window from the spell book window, by clicking the 'Research' button. It allows you to research new spells and to purify glyphs.</content>
<content type="pic" src="Cast Magic;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/>
<content type="text">With the 'Cast' button you can cast the currently discovered spell.</content>
<content type="pic" src="PurifyGlyphButton;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/>
<content type="text">The 'Purify' button allows you to purify glyphs. To use it you have to drag and drop a glyph on top of it. You will see the glyph changing its background after few seconds and a message in the chat window telling you the glyph is purified. Before researching a new spell you need to have your glyphs purified. Whenever your glyphs are given to an NPC or another player-character, when they are returned you will have to purify the glyphs again before you can use them to cast spells.</content>
<content type="pic" src="ResearchSpellButton;" padding="0" width="64" height="64"/>
<content type="text">The 'Research' button allows you to try the current glyph sequence and weave it into a spell. The glyphs should be placed in the empty slots just below the purify button, beginning with the left-most slot. If the sequence of glyphs corresponds to a spell and your research is successful, the new spell will be added to your spell book.</content></Contents>
</topic>
</branch>
<topic name="Stats and Skills window"><Contents><content type="text">At the top of this window you can see the current Health, Physical Stamina, Mana and Mental Stamina values of your character.

Below these values you can see all the stats, skills, and faction points of your character. You can switch between the different tabs to see the values of a specific category. If you see a number in brackets, it means this value is under magical influence (items, spells...) and the value in brackets is the current modified one. If you select one of the skills, you can see its description in the text window below.

At the bottom of the stats and skills window you can see the Progression Points (PPs) your character currently possesses, and how much more experience you need to get a new Progression Point. Next you have the amount of tria (money) you own, and two buttons for training.
There are three important parts to training a skill and improving the skill level.

Training can be divided between "stats" and "skills".

Training a skill is very simple. All you need to do is perform an action which gives you practice for the skill you want to train. Three examples of this are;
Casting a spell to practice magic.
Mining ores and gems to practice mining.
Fighting a creature while using a sword to train sword.

If you open your 'Stats and Skill' window you will see a bar with two colours. 'Red' is the total amount of practice you need to complete a level of training, and 'Green' which is the progress you have made to your next level. When the Red bar is filled by the Green bar then you have completed the amount of practice needed and your level is raised by 1 rank.

Training stats it is a little different. There are a total of six stats; Intelligence, Will, Charisma, Endurance, Strength, or Agility. Each of these is trained in the same way. You find an NPC which can train you in the stat you want to raise and you spend a combination of experience (which in PlaneShift is call Progression Points) and tria.

If you look in the 'Stats and Skill' window you will see the bars are different. The 'Yellow' bar indicates the amount of experience which you will need to spend on the next level, while the thin 'Blue' bar indicates how many practice points you have. When you have enough to buy the next level the blue bar will be the same length as the Yellow. At this point all you then need is enough tria to pay the trainer.

Experience (and Practice points, 1 Practice Point is 200 experience) is gained by doing exactly the same actions you perform to train a skill. As you are mining or fighting or casting magic, or performing any action you earn experience each time you complete the action. </content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="Commands"><Contents><content type="text">This section lists and explains all commands which can be typed into the chat window.</content></Contents>
<branch name="Alliance commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/allianceinvite"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can invite other guilds to your alliance. Only the leader of the guild that leads the alliance is able to do this.
Usage:
/allianceinvite [guild-leader]
(Invites the guild of [guild-leader] to the alliance.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/allianceleader"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can hand over the lead of the alliance to another guild. Only the current leader of the alliance is able to do this.
Usage:
/allianceleader [guild-name]
(Makes the guild with the name [guild-name] the leader of the alliance.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/allianceleave"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows your guild to leave an alliance. Only the guild leader is able to do this.
Usage:
/allianceleave
(Your guild leaves the alliance.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/allianceremove"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can remove guilds from your alliance. Only the leader of the alliance is able to do this.
Usage:
/allianceremove [guild-name]
(Removes the guild with the name [guild-name] from the alliance.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/endalliance"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can disband the current alliance. Only the leader of the alliance is able to do this.
Usage:
/endalliance
(Disbands the current alliance.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/newalliance"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can create a new alliance.
Usage:
/newalliance [alliance_name]
(Creates an alliance with the name [alliance_name].)</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="Chat related commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/alliance or /a"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can send messages to the Alliance chat. Your current guild must be member of an alliance to use this command.
Usage:
/alliance [message] 
/a [message]

Example;
/alliance Hello everyone.
/a Hello everyone
Writes "Hello everyone" to the Alliance chat. Can be combined with /me or /my.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/auction"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can write messages to the Auction chat tab.
Usage:
/auction [message]

Example;
/auction I have a selection of finely crafted weapons to sell.
Writes "I have a selection of finely crafted weapons to sell." to the Auction chat tab. Can be combined with /me and /my. Auction chat is IC and has a limited range, so please speak as your character, not your player self.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/away"><Contents><content type="text">Allows you to specify a reply message for every tell you get.
Usage:
/away [message]
This specifies the message sent to every player who sends you a tell. This can be useful in case you have to leave your computer for a while and want others to know you can't respond immediately.

/away on 
Without a message 'on' simply turns on the default away message.

/away off
/away
Either of these two commands will turn the away-message off again. Afterwards no automatic reply will be sent.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/clear"><Contents><content type="text">Use this command to clear the history of all or some of the chat window tabs.

Usage: 
/clear
This clears the history of the currently selected tab.

/clear all
This clears the history of all tabs.

/clear TabName
eg.
/clear main
Using this you can clear the text history of specific tabs. You can use any of these as the name of the tab to clear - main, channels or chat, npc, whisper or tell, guild, group, alliance, auction, system, help.</content></Contents></topic>
<branch name="/emote list"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can see a list of all possible emotes.
Usage:
/emote list
This writes a list of all possible emotes supported in the system chat tab.

/emote [emote-name]
/[emote-name]
Either one of these commands will have  your character do the emote. For example, "/emote agree" is the same as "/agree".

Please note that the emote text differs if you currently have a target selected. With a selected target the emote is usually directed at that target.

Possible emotes: agree, angry, beckon, beg, blush, bored, bow, catchbreath, charge, cheer, clap, cold, confused, cough, cry, curious, curse, dance, disappointed, drink, drunk, duck, excited, fear, flee, followme, glare, greet, grin, hungry, impatient, kiss, kneel, laugh, listen, nod, panic, point, poke, ponder, pounce, pout, pray, ready, roar, salute, shrug, shy, sigh, sleep, smile, sorry, stare, surprised, taunt, thank, volunteer, wave, wink, yawn.
Most of these emotes have no animation assigned to them yet and will just result in a message in the System chat window. But some, like greet, will also play an animation.)</content></Contents>
<topic name="/agree"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character nods. If you have a target selected, your character nods in agreement with the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/angry"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character shakes a fist in anger. If you have a target selected, your character shakes a fist in anger  at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/beckon"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character beckons everyone with a slight gesture of the hand. If you have a target selected, your character beckons the targeted character or object with a slight gesture of the hand.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/beg"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character gets down on the knees and begs. If you have a target selected, your character gets down on the knees and begs the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/blush"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character blushes. If you have a target selected, your character blushes at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/bored"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character taps a foot, obviously bored. If you have a target selected, your character taps a foot, obviously bored with the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/bow"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character makes a bow. If you have a target selected, your character makes a bow to the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/catchbreath"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character pants heavily, trying to catch a breath.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/charge"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character lets out a war cry and charges. If you have a target selected, your character lets out a war cry and charges towards the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/cheer"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character cheers happily. If you have a target selected, your character cheers happily at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/clap"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character claps. If you have a target selected, your character claps for the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/cold"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character shivers in the cold. If you have a target selected, your character shivers in the cold with the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/confused"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character looks around, confused. If you have a target selected, your character looks at the targeted character or object, confused.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/cough"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character lets out a wheezing cough. If you have a target selected, your character lets out a wheezing cough at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/cry"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character bursts into tears. If you have a target selected, your character bursts into tears on the shoulder of the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/curious"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character looks curious. If you have a target selected, your character looks curiously at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/curse"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character mutters curses. If you have a target selected, your character mutters curses at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/dance"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character begins to dance. If you have a target selected, your character grabs hold of the targeted character or object and begins to dance.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/disappointed"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character droops with disappointment. If you have a target selected, your character droops with disappointment at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/drink"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character raises a drink to the air before gulping it down. If you have a target selected, your character raises a drink to the targeted character or object before gulping it down.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/drunk"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character staggers around a bit, looking tipsy. If you have a target selected, your character staggers over and tries to grab hold of the targeted character or object but misses. Someone's had too much to drink!)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/duck"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character quickly ducks. If you have a target selected, your character quickly ducks from the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/excited"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character jumps around excitedly. If you have a target selected, your character jumps around excitedly at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/fear"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character quivers with a visible fear. If you have a target selected, your character quivers with a visible fear at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/flee"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character yells for everyone to flee. If you have a target selected, your character yells for the targeted character or object to flee.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/followme"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character motions for everyone to follow. If you have a target selected, your character motions for the targeted character or object to follow.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/glare"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character glares at everyone frostily. If you have a target selected, your character glares at the targeted character or object frostily.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/greet"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character greets everyone. If you have a target selected, your character greets the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/grin"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character grins impishly. If you have a target selected, your character grins at the targeted character or object impishly.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/hungry"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character glances around hungrily for something to eat. If you have a target selected, your character glances hungrily at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/impatient"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character fidgets impatiently. If you have a target selected, your character fidgets impatiently while waiting for the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/kiss"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character blows everyone a kiss. If you have a target selected, your character blows a kiss at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/kneel"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character kneels down before everyone. If you have a target selected, your character kneels down before the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/laugh"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character lets out a hearty laugh. If you have a target selected, your character laughs heartily at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/listen"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character listens intently. If you have a target selected, your character listens intently to the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/nod"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character nods. If you have a target selected, your character nods at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/panic"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character runs around in a slight panic. If you have a target selected, your character looks at the targeted character or object and panics.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/point"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character raises an arm and points. If you have a target selected, your character raises an arm and points towards the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/poke"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character pokes everyone nearby. If you have a target selected, your character pokes the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/ponder"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character ponders the situation. If you have a target selected, your character glances at the targeted character or object, pondering.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/pounce"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character pounces from the shadows. If you have a target selected, your character pounces on the targeted character or object from the shadows.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/pout"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character pouts. If you have a target selected, your character pouts at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/pray"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character concentrates in prayer. If you have a target selected, your character concentrates in prayer for the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/ready"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character stands ready. If you have a target selected, your character looks to see if the targeted character or object is ready.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/roar"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character lets out a thundering roar. If you have a target selected, your character lets out a thundering roar at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/salute"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character snaps to attention and salutes. If you have a target selected, your character salutes the targeted character or object with respect.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/shrug"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character shrugs casually. If you have a target selected, your character shrugs casually at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/shy"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character smiles shyly. If you have a target selected, your character smiles shyly at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/sigh"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character sighs dramatically. If you have a target selected, your character sighs dramatically at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/sleep"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character appears to have fallen asleep. If you have a target selected, your character falls asleep beside the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/smile"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character looks around smiling. If you have a target selected, your character smiles at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/sorry"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character apologizes to everyone. If you have a target selected, your character apologizes to the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/surprised"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character is taken aback with surprise. If you have a target selected, your character is taken aback with surprise at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/stare"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character stares at everyone with interest. If you have a target selected, your character stares at the targeted character or object with interest.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/taunt"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character taunts everyone mercilessly. If you have a target selected, your character taunts the targeted character or object mercilessly.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/thank"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character thanks everyone. If you have a target selected, your character thanks the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/volunteer"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character raises a hand in the air. If you have a target selected, your character looks at the targeted character or object and raises a hand.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/wave"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character waves. If you have a target selected, your character waves at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/wink"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character winks playfully. If you have a target selected, your character winks playfully at the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/yawn"><Contents><content type="text">(Your character tries to cover a yawn. If you have a target selected, your character tries to cover a yawn from the targeted character or object.)</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<topic name="/group or /gr"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to write messages to the Group chat if you are currently a member of a group.
Usage:
/group [message]
/gr [message]

Example;
/group Hello everyone.
/gr Hello everyone.
Writes "Hello everyone." to the Group chat. Can be combined with /me or /my.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guild or /g"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can send messages to your guild mates in the Guild chat.
Usage:
/guild [message]
/g [message]

Example;
/guild Hello guild.
/g Hello guild.
Writes "Hello guild." to the Guild chat. Can be combined with /me or /my.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/ignore"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to manage your Ignore list. If you put someone on your Ignore list, you won't see any chat text from them.
Usage:
/ignore
This opens the 'Ignore List' window. Click 'Add' and type in a player-character name, then click 'OK' to add the name to your Ignore list. To remove a player-character from the list, select the name from the list and click 'Remove'.

/ignore [character-name] add
Adds the player-character [character-name] to your ignore list.

/ignore [character-name] remove
Removes the player-character [character-name] from your ignore list.

/ignore [character-name]
Adds the player-character [character-name] to your ignore list if he/she/kra isn't on it already. Otherwise, removes him/her/kra from the list.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/join"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can join different chat channels. The names of these channels are displayed in the Chat/Channels tab of your chat-window e.g. Gossip.
Usage:
/join [channel-name]

Every time you join the game you automatically join the "Gossip" channel. To talk in this channel you say things like this;
/1 Hello everyone.

If you join a second channel;
/join Funny
Then you will join the channel with the name 'funny' and it will be given the first unused number. In this case '2'. To talk in this channel you need to use;
/2 Hello everyone.
Every additional channel you join will be given the next number, /3, /4, /5 etc.

</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/leave"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can leave chat-channels.
Usage:
/leave [channel-number]
Leaves the channel specified by the number [channel-number].</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/me"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to write self-defined emotes for your character. The starting /me will be replaced with your character's first name. The message is sent to the currently selected chat tab. This command can be combined with all commands that specify a chat tab, like /say, /shout, /tell, /auction...
Usage:
/me [message]

Example, if your name was 'Harnquist';
/me runs and jumps around.
Writes "Harnquist runs and jumps around." an emote defined by [message] starting with your character's first name to the currently selected chat tab.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/my"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can construct possessive emotes. The /my is replaced with "[char-name]'s". The message is sent to the currently selected chat tab. This command can be combined with all commands that specify a chat tab, like /say, /shout, /tell, /auction...
Usage:
/my [message]

Example, if your name was 'Harnquist';
/my eyes tear up after running and jumping around.
Writes "Harnquist's eyes tear up after running and jumping around." an emote starting with "[charname]'s" to the currently selected chat tab.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/mypet"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can describe actions of your pet. The /mypet is replaced with the name of your pet.
Usage:
/mypet [message]

Example with a pet called 'drifter';
/mypet bites Harnquist.
Sends the message "Drifter bites Harnquist." to Main chat starting with the name of your pet.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/say or /s"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to write text to Main chat. As with every channel, if you already have the Main chat tab selected, you may just type directly into the chat window without the need for '/say'.
Usage:
/say [message] 
/s [message]

Example;
/say Can you help me?
/s Can you help me?
Writes "Can you help me?" to Main chat. Can be combined with /me or /my.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/shout or /sh"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to shout in Main chat, making yourself heard beyond the normal speaking range. The use of /shout should be kept to a minimum and the command is not suitable for normal conversations.
Usage:
/shout [message]

/shout I need help!
Shouts "I need help!" in Main chat. Can be combined with /me or /my.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/tell or /t"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to send tells to another player in Whisper chat.
Usage:
/tell [char-name] [message]

/tell Harnquist Hi, how are you.
Sends the player called "Harnquist" the text "Hi, how are you." Can be combined with /me or /my.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/tellnpc"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can communicate with NPCs in NPC chat.
Usage:
/tellnpc [message]

Example;
/tellnpc Give me a quest.
Sends the currently selected NPC the text "Give me a quest." in NPC chat.</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="Combat commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/assist"><Contents><content type="text">Targets the same target as another player.
Usage:
/assist [Char-name]
Makes the target of the specified character your own target. If no name was specified the currently targeted player is used. This command works only for characters either in your guild or your current group.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/attack"><Contents><content type="text">Attacks a target.
Usage:
/attack [Attack-stance]

Example;
/attack bloody
Attacks your current target with the 'bloody' stance. Possible stances are: bloody, aggressive, normal, defensive and fully defensive. Omit the space when writing the last i.e. /attack fullydefensive. If no stance is given, normal is used for the attack.)

/attack lower
Lowers your current attack stance, for example from normal to defensive or from bloody to aggressive. If used when not already attacking, this command simply commences attack on your current target in the default normal stance.

/attack raise
Raises your current attack stance, for example from normal to aggressive or from aggressive to bloody. If used when not already attacking, this command simply commences attack on your current target in the default normal stance.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/cast"><Contents><content type="text">Allows your character to cast magic spells.
Usage:
/cast [power] [spellname]

Example;
/cast 50 flame burst
Casts the spell "flame burst", provided your character has researched and discovered the spell, i.e. it is listed in your spell book. [power] is a value between 1 and 100 which defines the strength of the spell. If [power] is not given, the value indicated by the slider in the Information window is used.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/challenge"><Contents><content type="text">Sends a challenge request to another player.
Usage:
/challenge
Challenges the currently targeted character to a duel. The System chat tab will show you if the other player accepted or rejected the challenge.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/loot"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can loot corpses of NPCs. You can't loot another player after a duel.
Usage:
/loot [roll] [all|money|items [categories]]
Attempts to loot targeted NPC, taking specified goods. If no specifics are provided, a loot window will show up.

/loot
Opens the loot window of the current target. You can loot items by clicking on them and then clicking the 'take item' button.

/loot money
Loots all the tria from the dead target creature. If you're in a group, the tria will be shared

/loot [roll] items [categories]
Loots money and items with specified categories (e.g. "/loot item weapons - axe" or "/loot items weapons - axe, shields, animal parts). If no categories are mentioned then all items will be looted. If you add the optional "roll" before "items" (e.g. "/loot roll item weapons - axe"), all specified items will be rolled. You can get a list of current categories by looking at the names when you buy/sell items from a merchant. You can also use part of a category name, 'weapon' will loot any category beginning with 'weapon' (e.g. "/loot item weapon") and 'armor' will loot any category beginning with 'armor'(e.g. "/loot item armor").

/loot [roll] all
Loots everything, money and all items. If you're in a group, money will be shared and items are either taken or rolled, if you add the optional "roll" before "all".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/stopattack"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can stop your current attack.
Usage:
/stopattack
Stops the current attack.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/target"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to specify a target.
Usage:
/target [Player-name]
Targets the player with the name [Player-name]. Also works if just the first three letters of [Player-name] are typed after /target.

/target [Item-name]
Targets the item with the name [Item-name]. Also works if just the first three letters of [Item-name] are typed after /target.]

/target next [category]
Makes the next target of type [category] your current target. Possible values for [category] are: npc, pc (Player Character), player, alive, dead, item, any.

/target prev [category]
Makes the previous target of type [category] your current target. Possible values for [category] are: npc, pc (Player Character), player, alive, dead, item, any.

/target nearest [category]
Makes the nearest target of type [category] your current target. Possible values for [category] are: npc, pc (Player Character), player, alive, dead, item, any.

/target clear
Clears your current target and leaves you with nothing targeted at all.

/target self
Targets your own character.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/yield"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to yield in a duel.
Usage:
/yield
(Surrenders to your opponent in a duel.)</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="Crafting commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/combine"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to combine items in an container. The items must first be placed in the container and the container must be targeted. Depending on what you want to combine, it might be necessary to have an appropriate tool equipped.
Usage:
/combine
Combines the items in a targeted container.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/dig"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can dig for ores and other resources. You need a rockpick equipped in your right hand to be able to dig, and you need to find the location of your desired resource.
Usage:
/dig
Digs for resources at your current position. If you successfully obtain a resource, the spot will be exhausted and you will have to move a pace or a few paces before digging again.

/dig [resource]
Allows you to specify your desired resource. This is useful when there is more than one resource that can be mined at that location.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/fish"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can fish in rivers and lakes.
Usage:
/fish
This fishes at your current position. If you make a successful catch, the spot will be exhausted and you will have to move a pace or a few paces before fishing again.

/fish [fish-type]
Allows you to specify your desired catch. This is useful when there is more than one type of catch available at that location.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/harvest"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to harvest plants without having to wait for them to respawn. For this, you will need a harvesting tool equipped.
Usage:
/harvest
Harvests plants at your current position. If you harvest successfully, the spot will be exhausted and you will have to move a pace or a few paces before harvesting again.

/harvest [plant-name]
Allows you to specify your desired harvest. This is useful when there is more than one plant that can be harvested at that location.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/repair"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can repair damaged weapons and armor. In order to repair weapons, a weapons repair kit is needed. For armor, your need an armor repair kit. One of those kits is used up upon every execution of /repair.
Usage:
/repair [slot-name]
Repairs the item in the specified slot. If no slot is specified, the item in your right hand will be repaired. Possible values for [slot-name]: righthand, lefthand, helm, legs, boots, torso, gloves, arms.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/takeall"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can move all items from a targeted container to your inventory.
Usage:
/takeall
Moves all items within the targeted container to your inventory. Only those of identical quality will automatically be stacked within the same slot.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/takestackall"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can pick up a number of items from a targeted container and have them stacked within the same slot in your inventory.
Usage:
/takestackall
Moves all items within the targeted container to your inventory and stacks all of the same item type within the same slot.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/use"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can use an item.
Usage:
/use [item-name]
Uses a targeted tool or container, such as an anvil or forge.

/use [inventory-item]
/use [stack-count] [slot] [item-name]
Functions like the /equip command, allowing your character equip a specified item from your inventory to one of your avatar slots, e.g. /use 65 lefthand Iron Arrow. If you /use an edible/potable item, however, your character simply eats/drinks the item.</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="Group commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/disband"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to disband a group. Only the leader of a group is able to do this.
Usage:
/disband
Disbands the current group.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/groupleader"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can change the group leader to another member of the group, provided you are the leader of the group.
Usage:
/groupleader [char-name]
Changes the group leader to the group member with the name [char-name].</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/groupremove"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can remove characters from a group, provided you are the leader of the group.
Usage:
/groupremove [char-name]
Removes the character with the name [char-name] from the group.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/groupmembers"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can list all members of your current group.
Usage:
/groupmembers
Prints the names of all members of your current group to your System chat.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/groupchallenge"><Contents><content type="text">With this command the group leader may challenge another group to a duel. Only the other group's leader may accept.
Usage:
/groupchallenge [char-name]
Challenges the group of [char-name] to a duel.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/groupyield"><Contents><content type="text">With this command the group leader may yield to the opposing group in a duel.
Usage:
/groupyield
Yields to the other group in a group duel.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/invite"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can invite other characters to your group, provided you are the group leader.
Usage:
/invite [char-name]
Invites the character with the name [char-name] to the group.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/leavegroup"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can leave a group.
Usage:
/leavegroup
Leaves your current group.</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="Guild commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/endguild"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can disband your current guild. Only the guild leader is able to do this.
Usage:
/endguild [your-guild-name]
Disbands your guild.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/getmemberpermissions"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can see the permissions that the specified guild member has, provided you have editing privileges enabled and the specified member is of a lower rank than you.
Usage:
/getmemberpermissions [member-name]
Allows you to see the permissions that the specified guild member has.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildinfo or /show guild"><Contents><content type="text">This command opens the guild window.
Usage:
/guildinfo or /show guild
Opens the guild window, provided you are currently in a guild.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildinvite"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to invite new members to your guild, provided your guild rank has the required permission to invite members.
Usage:
/guildinvite [char-name]
(Invites the character with the name [char-name] to your guild.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildlevel"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows the guild leader to rename the different guild ranks.
Usage:
/guildlevel [rank] [new-name]
Gives [rank] the new name [new-name]. [Rank] is a number from 1 to 9.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildmembers"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can list all members of your guild.
Usage:
/guildmembers [rank]
Lists all members of your guild with the rank [rank] in your System chat. [rank] is a number from 1 to 9. If [rank] is not specified, all members will be listed.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildmotd"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can view or change the current MOTD of your guild, if you have the "pub notices" privilege enabled for your rank.
Usage:
/guildmotd [new-motd]
Sets the MOTD of your guild to [new-motd]. If no [new-motd] is given the old MOTD will be printed to your System chat.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildname"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to change the guild name if your guild rank has the appropriate permissions.
Usage:
/guildname [new-name]
Changes the name of your guild to [new-name].</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildpromote"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can promote guild members, provided your guild rank has the appropriate permissions enabled. You may only promote others to a rank lower than yours.
Usage:
/guildpromote [char-name] [rank]
Promotes the character [char-name] to the rank [rank]. [rank] is a number from 1 to 9.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildremove"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to remove characters from your guild, provided your guild rank has the appropriate permissions enabled.
Usage:
/guildremove [char-name]
Removes the character with the name [char-name] from the guild. If no character is specified, you will remove yourself from the guild.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildsecret"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can toggle if your guild is set as secret or not. Your rank must have editing permissions for this to work.
Usage:
/guildsecret
Without any parameters the current status is printed to your System chat.

/guildsecret on
Makes your guild a secret guild.

/guildsecret off
Makes your guild a public guild.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildwar"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to ask another guild for a guild war. Only the leader of a guild is able to do this and only the leader of the other guild is able to accept.
Usage:
/guildwar
Challenges the currently targeted guild leader's guild to a guild war.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildweb"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can set the URL for your guild's webpage. Your current rank must allow you editing permissions for this to work.
Usage:
/guildweb [URL]
Sets the guild webpage to [URL].</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildyield"><Contents><content type="text">With this command your guild can yield to another guild in a guild war. Only the guild leader may do this and only the leader of the other guild may accept.
Usage:
/guildyield
Surrenders to the guild of the targeted guild leader.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/newguild"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can create a new guild. Creating a guild will cost you tria, and you must also have at least 5 characters join in the first few minutes or the guild will automatically disband.
Usage:
/newguild [guild-name]
Creates a new guild with the name [guild-name].</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/setmemberpermissions"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can set or change the permissions that the specified guild member has, provided you have editing permissions enabled and the specified member is of a lower rank than you.
Usage:
/setmemberpermissions [member-name] [view_chat | chat | invite | remove | promote | edit_level | edit_points | edit_guild | edit_public | edit_private | alliance_view_chat | alliance_chat | guild_bank]
Allows you to set or change the permissions that the specified guild member has.</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="Help channel commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/advice"><Contents><content type="text">With this command, advisors can answer in the help channel.
Usage:
/advice [charname] [message]

Once you advise a player, he/she is assigned to you and only you can reply to follow-up questions. Such a help session ends either if one of the participants quits the game or some minutes after the last typed text. Once you "claim" a help session you will be reminded in your System chat if there is still a question you haven't replied to.

There is an invisible advisor point system in place that awards advisor points per account. This means that any/all of the (up to) four characters on your account accumulates advisor points not individually but to that account. These points are relevant if you plan to apply for the GM team. GMs and Devs can check the number of advisor-points you have.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/advisor"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to check the current status of the Help channel as well as to change your own advisor settings.
Usage:
/advisor
Prints your advisor status to your System chat, i.e. tells you whether you are currently an advisor or not.

/advisor list
Lists the number of current advisors in the Help channel. You don't have to be an advisor yourself to see how many there are

/advisor requests
Repeats the last question in the Help channel. This can be useful so that you do not miss any help request, or to see if there was a help request before you became an advisor. Only usable if you are an advisor

/advisor sessions
Lists all help sessions currently assigned to you. You need to be an advisor to be able to use this.

/advisor on
Makes you an advisor for the Help channel. You can only become an advisor if you have played at least 30 hours on this account. Also make sure you understand the rules of the Help channel before becoming an advisor

/advisor off
With this you can end your role as advisor for the Help channel. There is no point remaining in the Help channel if you are currently busy in game or afk. This will only lead to players looking for help but not getting an answer in the Help channel.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/help"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can ask questions in the Help channel.
Usage:
/help [question]
Asks [question] in the Help channel. In case no advisor is currently available, you are notified in your System chat.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/petition"><Contents><content type="text">This command creates a petition, which is a request addressed to a GM.
Usage:
/petition [message]
Submits a petition with the text [message].</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="Interaction commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/bank"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to open the banking window. A banker NPC must be targeted for this to work.
Usage:
/bank personal
Opens the personal banking window of your character. Here you can deposit and/or withdraw money belonging to your character as well as exchange coins

/bank guild
This opens the banking window for your guild and allows you to deposit and/or withdraw guild funds. For this, you must have guild banking privileges enabled.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/buy"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to open the merchant window for a specific selling NPC.
Usage:
/buy
Opens the merchant window for the selected NPC in buy-mode.

/buy [NPC-name]
Opens the merchant window for the specified NPC in buy-mode.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/give"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can give items to other players or NPCs. Containers (like sacks) cannot be traded at the moment. However, your character may drop the container for another player-character to pick up.
Usage:
/give
Opens the trading window for the selected player-character or NPC.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/marriage"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows your character to marry or divorce. It's only possible to marry someone of a different gender.
Usage:
/marriage propose [first-name] [message]
Proposes to the specified character. You must obtain his/her consent for marriage

/marrriage divorce [message]
Divorces your current spouse, pending his/her consent.

If you find you are married and the player has not played for a few months you can ask a GM divorce you.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/npcmenu"><Contents><content type="text">This command opens the dialogue menu for NPCs. This menu will not be available to you if the NPC has no quests for your character at the time.
Usage:
/npcmenu
Opens the talk-menu for the currently selected NPC.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/sell"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to open the merchant window for a specific NPC. For this, the selected or specified NPC must be a buying NPC.
Usage:
/sell
Opens the merchant window for the selected NPC in sell-mode.

/sell [NPC-name]
Opens the merchant window for the specified NPC in sell-mode.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/storage"><Contents><content type="text">Opens the storage window for the currently targeted storage manager NPC.
Usage:
/storage
Opens the storage window for the selected NPC. Note that your storage can be accessed through any storage manager NPC.

/storage [NPC-name]
Opens the storage window for the specified NPC. Note that your storage can be accessed through any storage manager NPC.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/study"><Contents><content type="text">Opens a crafting book in another window for easier reading.
Usage:
/study
This command opens the Study notes window and is useful when you have a crafting book from your inventory or mind slot open and want the text in a more readable display. If no book is open, the Study notes window will be blank, or will display the crafting book that was last open in the current game session.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/trade"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to start a trade with another player-character.
Usage:
/trade
Asks the currently selected player-character for a trade and opens the trading window if he/she/kra accepts.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/train"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can open the training window of a trainer NPC.
Usage:
/train
Opens the training window for the currently selected NPC. Only works if the NPC is a trainer.</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="Item commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/dequip"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to unequip items.
Usage:
/dequip [item-name]
Unequips the specified item. The item will be placed back in your inventory. If there is more than one item with this name equipped, the first found will be unequipped.

/dequip [slot]
Unequips an item for the specified slot. Possible values for [slot] are: righthand, lefthand, helm, legs, boots, bracers, torso, gloves, neck, rightfinger, leftfinger, belt, arms, back, or mind. The items will be placed back in your inventory.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/drop"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to drop an item (or a stack of items of the same kind).
Usage:
/drop [quantity | all] [any] [noguard] [inplace] [item-name]

Example;
/drop apple
/drop 5 apple
/drop all appl
/drop noguard apple
/drop inplace apple

This drops the specified [quantity] of the specified item. If no [quantity] is given, one item will be dropped. If [quantity] is "all", as many items as possible, up to a maximum of 65, are dropped. If [any] is added after the [quantity], items from containers such as sacks are dropped also. By adding [noguard], anyone around can pick up the item. Otherwise, by default the item is guarded and only you are able to pick it up again. With [inplace] the item is dropped at your character position. Without [inplace] the item is dropped right in front of your character.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/equip"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to equip items from your inventory.
Usage:
/equip [quantity] [slot] [item-name]
Equips the specified [quantity] of an item with the name [item-name] to the appropriate slot or the one specified. Possible values for [slot] are: righthand, lefthand, helm, legs, boots, bracers, torso, gloves, neck, rightfinger, leftfinger, belt, arms, back and mind. If no [quantity] is given, one item will be equipped. If you have several items with the name [item-name] in your inventory, the first found will be equipped.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guard"><Contents><content type="text">With this command, you can unguard items dropped by you. Once an item is unguarded, it's not possible to re-guard it without picking up the item again.
Usage:
/guard
Unguards the selected item.

Additional info:
Even if the name of the command implies so, it is not possible for ordinary players to guard items by using it. Only the GM/dev version of this command has that function.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/pickup"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can pick up an item, but only if it is not guarded by someone else.
Usage:
/pickup
Picks up the currently selected item.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/rotate"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to rotate objects. If the target name contains spaces, it must be specified within single inverted commas (single quotation marks), e.g. /rotate 'Iron Arrow' 90 90 90
Usage:
/rotate [target] [x] [y] [z]
Rotates the specified target along the x, y and z axis. The angles must be given in degrees. If no target is specified, the currently targeted object will be used.

/rotate [target] [axis] [angle]
Rotates the specified target along one axis. Possible values for [axis] are: x, y, z. The angle must be given in degrees. If no target is specified, the currently targeted object will be used.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/write"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can open the Book Writing window for a book equipped to your character. If the book title contains spaces, it must be specified within single inverted commas (single quotation marks), e.g. /write 'A Tale of Two Cities'
Usage:
/write [item-name]
Opens the Book Writing window for the book with the name [item-name

/write [slot]
Opens the Book Writing window for the items equipped in [slot]. Possible [slots] are: righthand, lefthand.</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="Miscellaneous commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/? or /show help"><Contents><content type="text">This command opens the Help window.
Usage:
/? or /show help
Opens the Help window.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/brightness"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to change the brightness level.
Usage:
/brightness [value|increase|decrease|reset]

Sets a brightness value between -1.0 and 3.0. Entering /brightness increase or decrease will change the brightness by 0.1. Reset makes it revert to 0.0. By default, F10 will reset, F11 decrease and F12 increase brightness as well.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/buddy"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to manage your buddy-list.
Usage:
/buddy or /show buddy
Opens the Friends window.

/buddy [char-name] add
Adds the specified character to your buddy list.

/buddy [char-name] remove
Removes the specified character from your buddy list.

/buddy [char-name]
Adds the specified character if he/she/kra isn't on your list already otherwise removes him/her/kra.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/confirm"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to display a confirmation window and execute the commands defined in the 'yes' or 'no' fields for that window.
Usage:
/confirm [message] [yes-command] [no-command]
Displays a confirmation window with the text [message] and a "yes" and "no" button. [yes-command] is executed if 'yes' is clicked; otherwise [no-command] gets executed. Type messages or commands that include spaces within single inverted commas or single quotation marks.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/deputize"><Contents><content type="text">Reserved for Game Master use.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/die"><Contents><content type="text">This command will make your character die. This is mainly for roleplaying a death, gaining access to the Death Realm or debugging and in case your character is stuck, the /unstick command does not work and you can't get hold of a GM to help you out.
Usage:
/die
Makes your character die. You will respawn either in Hydlaa or in the Death Realm depending on how long you have been playing the game. New characters do not go to the Death Realm for the first 15 hours.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/echo"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to have a message appear in System chat.
Usage:
/echo [message]
Writes the message to your System chat.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/fps"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to toggle the display of the current graphics performance of PlaneShift in frames per second.
Usage:
/fps
Toggles the display, in the top lefthand corner of the client window, of the current graphics performance of PlaneShift in frames per second add prints that number into the system tab.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/game"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to play on the gameboards in PS. You need to have the gameboard selected.
Usage:
/game
Starts a game session on the selected gameboard. Two players can use one board at the same time.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/graphicbug"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can write a bug-report for graphic errors which makes it easier for developers to identify your problem.
Usage:
/graphicbug
Saves your camera position to enable you to reproduce what you saw. You might then use this information to report a bug in textures, buildings, etc.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/loadDesc"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can load a new description for your character from a file. The text files for the descriptions must be in the [config-directory]/descriptions folder but don't have to follow the [char-name]_description.txt format. Any filename will do here.
Usage:
/loadDesc [filename]
Loads the description from the file [filename] and sets it as your current description.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/loadOOCDesc"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can load a new OOC description for your character from a file. The text files for the descriptions must be in the [config-directory]/descriptions folder but don't have to follow the [char-name]_description.txt format. Any filename will do here.
Usage:
/loadOOCDesc [filename]
Loads the description from the file [filename] and sets it as your current OOC description.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/loadshortcuts"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can load a new collection of shortcuts from those saved in your user data folder. The text files for the descriptions must be in the [config-directory]/options folder but don't have to follow the shortcutcommands_[char-name].xml format. 

Usage:
/loadshortcuts [filename]
Loads the collection of shortcuts from the file [filename] and sets them as you current shortcuts.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/motd"><Contents><content type="text">Get the MOTD of the server.
Usage:
/motd
This will request the server's MOTD and write it to your System chat.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/picklock"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to pick locks of doors and chests. Not yet implemented.
Usage:
/picklock
(Picks the lock of your current target.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/ping"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can get the current latency of your connection.
Usage:
/ping
Writes the ping rate to your System chat.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/pos"><Contents><content type="text">This command prints your current position and the map you are in at the moment. This is mainly useful for debugging and bug reports. If you report a graphic bug for example it's usually a good idea to include the output of /pos in your report so that the developers can easily find the place you talk about.
Usage:
/pos
Prints the position and the map to your System chat.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/quit"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can leave PlaneShift.
Usage:
/quit
Brings up a confirmation dialogue box asking if you want to end the game and quits PlaneShift if you click "yes".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/reload"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to reintialize a function in case it is not working properly or changes have been made since startup.
Usage:
/reload shortcut
Reloads the contents of "shortcutcommands.xml" in order to employ its changes since the start of the current game session.

/reload sound
Reinitializes music files for the current "Sound Sector".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/repaintlabels"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to reload the labels displayed above items, NPCs and player characters.
Usage:
/repaintlabels
Recreates the labels displayed above items, NPCs and player characters.

/repaintlabels force
Reloads the labels displayed above items, NPCs and player characters.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/replay"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to reprint a specified portion of the chat logs to the Chat window.
/replay [count]
Reprints the portion of the chat logs specified by [count] to the current Chat window, where [count] is the number of previous lines you would like reprinted. For example, /replay 1 reprints the last line displayed, /replay 2 reprints the last two lines, and so on.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/report"><Contents><content type="text">With this command the server logs all actions done by the player you are reporting, about 5 minutes on either side of your executing the command. This is useful for providing proof to GMs investigating the rude behaviour, offensive language, cheating, or other alleged misbehaviour of a player.
Usage:
/report [playername]
Keeps a log of the specified player. No notice is given to the player that his actions are going to be logged.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/rndmsgtest"><Contents><content type="text">Reserved for testing purposes.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/roll"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can roll dice with everyone near seeing the outcome.
Usage:
/roll [times] [sides] [minvalue]

Example:
/roll
This will roll a die or dice and print the outcome in base-system, visible for everyone near you. Using /roll without any parameter will lead to rolling one six-sided die.
/roll 6
If you specify one number after /roll you will roll one die with the sides specified by that number, in this case a 6 sided dice.
/roll 2 6
 By giving two numbers after /roll, you will roll as many dice as specified by the first number with as many sides as specified by the second number. In this case you will roll 2 6 sided dice.
/roll 2 6 6
By adding a third number to the command you will get also told how often you scored a result equal to or larger than the last number. In this example you will roll 2 6 sided dice and you will be told how many time a number equal or greater than 6 was scored.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/saveshortcuts"><Contents><content type="text">This will allow you to save your current collection of shortcuts to a file name which you can then load using another character.

Usage:
/saveshortcuts [filename]

This will save your current selection of shortcuts to the name you have defined as long as it does not exist. If it does you need to load that shortcut file and then edit it. Edits will automatically be saved to the file you loaded.
</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/screenshot"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can take screenshots.
Usage:
/screenshot [lossless] [nogui]

Example;
/screenshot
/screenshot lossless
/screenshot nogui
/screenshot lossless nogui
Takes a screenshot of your current screen. If "lossless" is used the image gets saved as a PNG file otherwise as a JPEG file. If "nogui" is given, the screenshot will be without the Graphical User Interface (i.e. without any windows or chat boxes). Otherwise all interface elements are contained in the screenshot.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/setDesc"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can change the description of your character.
Usage:
/setDesc [new-desc]
Overwrites your old description and sets it to [new-desc]. Every "\n" in [new-desc] sets a line break.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/setOOCDesc"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can change the OOC description of your character.
Usage:
/setOOCDec [new-desc]
Overwrites your old OOC description and sets it to [new-desc]. Every "\n" in [new-desc] sets a line break.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/show"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can open and close specific windows.
Usage:
/show [windowname]
Opens the window with the name [windowname]. If the window was already opened it is closed again. Possible names are: activemagic, bag, buddy, buy, chat, communications, craft, detail, exchange, glyph, group, guild, help, ignore, info, inv, inventory, loot, merchant, music, options, petition, petitions, quest, questreward, quit, read, shortcut, sketch, skills, smallinventory, 'spell book', spells, stats, talk, write.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/sit"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows your character to sit down.
Usage:
/sit
Your character sits at his current position.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/stand"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows your character to stand up again. (Not possible if your character is overloaded.)
Usage:
/stand
Your character stands up again.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/starttrading"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can allow trades after a previous /stoptrading again.
Usage:
/starttrading
Allows others to trade with you.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/stoptrading"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can prevent all other players from starting a trade with you.
Usage:
/stoptrading
Blocks all incoming trades from other players.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/targetcontext"><Contents><content type="text">This command opens the context-menu for the selected target. This is the same menu you would get if you right-click the target.
Usage:
/targetcontext or /targetcontext [target]
Opens the context menu for the selected or specified target.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/targetinfo"><Contents><content type="text">This command opens the details-window for the selected target. This is useful if the targetted player-character or NPC is out of range and right-clicking does not bring up the 'EXAMINE' icon.
Usage:
/targetinfo
Opens the details-window with information about the selected player or NPC.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/testanim"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to test animation. No other player will see the animation.
Usage:
/testanim [name] [fade-in] [fade-out]
Plays the animation [name]. [fade-in] is the amount of seconds it should take to morph from your current animation to the animation you want to test. [fade-out] is the time it should take to go back to your original animation after the test animation finished.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/tip"><Contents><content type="text">This command requests a tip from the server.
Usage:
/tip
Gets a tip from the server and writes it to the system chat tab.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/togglerun"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to switch between the running and walking (current movement) state of your character.
Usage:
/togglerun
Toggles between moving and running. If your character was walking the character will now be running and if your character was running the character will now be walking

/togglerun walk
Puts the character in the walk state. If your character was already walking nothing happens.

/togglerun run
Puts the character in the run state. If your character was already running nothing happens.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/unstick"><Contents><content type="text">This command might help you when your character is stuck in the 3D environment. In some cases it can move your character back to a valid location.
Usage:
/unstick
Moves your character back to a valid location, if possible. Before using this command, make sure that your character is really stuck i.e. first, try the arrow and spacebar keys to dislodge your character. If all fails, try relogging, typing /die or contacting a GM in game.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/version"><Contents><content type="text">This command prints out the current version of the PlaneShift client.
Usage:
/version
Writes the current version to the system chat tab.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/who"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to list characters that are currently online.
Usage:
/who [filter]
Lists characters whose name or whose guild contain the expression specified by [filter]. If no [filter] is given, all online characters are listed up to a pre-determined character limit.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/window"><Contents><content type="text">With this command you can get the current position and size of a window, set window positions, get all window names and positions, and show/hide windows.

Usage
/window [list|name|all] [getinfo|setposition|setsize|show|hide] [x] [y]

/window list
This lists all the window names and their alternative names in the system tab.

/window [name] getinfo
/window all getinfo
This will list the position and size for the named window, or for all windows

/window [name] setposition x y 
This sets the position of the named window to the position x y relative to the top left corner of the game screen.

/window [name] setsize x y 
This sets the size of the named window to the size x y.

/window [name] show
This shows the named window

/window [name] hide
This hides the named window.</content></Contents></topic>
<!--
<branch name="Unimplemented or Suspended Commands"><Contents><content type="text">The following commands have either yet to be implemented or have been withdrawn.</content></Contents>
<topic name="/admin"><Contents><content type="text">This command lists the available admin commands for your account. As I assume your are no GM or Dev this won't do anything for you.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/construct"><Contents><content type="text">(To be implemented.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guildpoints"><Contents><content type="text">This command shows the karma points of your guild. Guild karma increases if an enemy guild surrenders to your guild.
Usage:
/guildpoints [guild-name]
(Prints the specified guild's karma points to your System chat.)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/introduce"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to introduce your character to others.
Usage:
/introduce
(Introduces your character to the selected target or everyone around if no target is selected.)
Additional Info:
In the past there was an introduction system in place that allowed you to see only the names of people you were already acquainted with. All other characters were visible only as generic descriptions e.g. Somebody. Due to flaws, the system was withdrawn for the confusion that ensued when multiple 'unknown' characters were interacting. It might be re-implemented if a way is found to rectify the flaws.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/tellnpcinternal"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/uncombine"><Contents><content type="text">(To be implemented)</content></Contents></topic></branch>
-->
</branch>
<branch name="Pet commands"><Contents><content type="text"></content></Contents>
<topic name="/mount"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to mount an animal. Not all available pets can be mounted. Sitting on a yulbar is more likely to kill the poor little creature than help you travel faster.
Usage:
/mount
Mounts the currently selected pet. You must be the owner of the pet for this to work. Also allows you to dismount as long as you have no target selected.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/pet"><Contents><content type="text">This is the main command for interaction with your pets.
All of the following commands apply to the currently summoned pet. The summon command takes one additional argument where [pet-name] is either the first name of your pet or its number. If no [pet-name] is given, the first pet of the ones you own is summoned.
Usage:
/pet assist
This makes your pet assist you in combat by attacking your current target.
/pet attack
Your pet will attack your current target.
/pet dismiss
This dismisses your pet.
/pet follow
Your pet will follow you wherever you go.
/pet guard
Your pets guards its current position.
/pet name [new-name]
Renames your pet to [new-name].
/pet run
Commands your pet to run instead of walking.
/pet stay
Your pet will stay at its current position and not follow you any more.
/pet stopattack
Your pet stops attacking your current target.
/pet summon [pet-name]
Summons your pet. You need to have the necessary item equipped for this to work.
/pet target [target]
Sets the target of your pet. If no target is given, the target of your character will be used. If [target] is "me", your pet will target your character. Otherwise, [target] is interpreted as the name of the target you want to set.
/pet walk
Commands your pet to walk instead of running.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/unmount"><Contents><content type="text">This command allows you to unmount an animal.
Usage:
/unmount
Unmounts from the currently mounted mount. You must be mounted for this to work.</content></Contents></topic></branch></branch>
<branch name="Files"><Contents><content type="text">This is a collection of files and directories that you can use to customise PlaneShift, import and export textual data, for example to move or debug your configuration files, copy/revise chat logs, load and save in game books, etc.</content></Contents>
<branch name="Configuration Files"><Contents><content type="text">Depending on your operating system, the configuration files of PlaneShift can be found here:

Windows: %AppData%\PlaneShift
(%AppData% is a shortcut to the user files of windows, just type it in the address bar of the windows explorer)

Mac: ~/Library/Application Support/PlaneShift
(~ is your home directory)

Linux: ~/.PlaneShift
(~ is your home directory)</content></Contents>
<topic name="planeshift.cfg"><Contents><content type="text">The basic configuration file for PlaneShift.

Most of these settings can be changed in the pslaunch application. This file also contains the saved username and password for login. The positions of the in-game windows are saved in this file as well, so if you managed to move a window off the screen somehow and can't get it back , just delete this file and all positions will be set to default again.

Additional Info:
By adding a "PlaneShift.Loading.ForceCuller = default" line to this file, the hardware culler can be enabled. At the moment this still causes some minor graphical errors but in general increases the performance a lot. So might be worth trying out if you experience very bad performance.
For self-compiled clients: With "System.Plugins.iMovieRecorder = crystalspace.utilities.movierecorder" you can enable the movie recorder plugin from CrystalSpace. Check the CrystalSpace webpage for instructions on how to use it.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="shadercache"><Contents><content type="text">This file keeps pre-compiled versions of the shaders used by PlaneShift.
Usually there is no reason to touch this file, but if you experience crashes (especially after an update) it might be worth trying to delete this file and get PlaneShift to recompile all shaders again.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="updaterinfo.xml"><Contents><content type="text">This file contains information about the updates you performed with this version of PlaneShift. DO NOT TOUCH!</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="updateservers.xml"><Contents><content type="text">This file contains the addresses of the update server(s). DO NOT TOUCH!</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<branch name="User files"><Contents><content type="text">Depending on your system the user files of PlaneShift can be found here:
Windows: %AppData%\PlaneShift
(%AppData% is a shortcut to the user files of windows, just type it in the address bar of the windows explorer)
Mac: ~/Library/Application Support/PlaneShift
(~ is your home directory)
Linux: ~/.PlaneShift
(~ is your home directory)</content></Contents>
<topic name="Books"><Contents><content type="text">The "books" subdirectory of your PlaneShift configuration directory contains all the text files of books you saved in game. In case you want to write a book with an editor outside of PlaneShift just save the book to this directory with a .txt extension. In game, type the name of the file (including the .txt) to load it.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Character descriptions"><Contents><content type="text">The "descriptions" subdirectory of your PlaneShift configuration directory contains your saved character descriptions. The Character window in game saves and loads files in the form FORENAME_LASTNAME_description.txt. The /loadDesc and /loadOOCDesc commands take a filename as argument and enable you to load different description files.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Chat logs"><Contents><content type="text">The "logs" subdirectory of your PlaneShift configuration directory contains the chat logs of your characters. The default filename is "FORENAME_LASTNAME_chat.txt". You can change in the in-game options what chat channels get logged and in what file they should be written.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Screenshots"><Contents><content type="text">The "screenshots" subdirectory of your PlaneShift configuration directory contains all the screenshots you made in game with the /screenshot command.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="Sketches"><Contents><content type="text">The "sketches" subdirectory of your PlaneShift configuration directory contains all map-sketches you save in game.</content></Contents></topic></branch></branch>
<branch name="GM Commands" level="1"><Contents><content type="text">Commands available to game master level characters.  Note that this is a full list of abilities, and not all access groups have everything listed here.</content></Contents>
<branch name="General Syntax"><Contents><content type="text">Commands which act on a target all use the same system.  A number of keywords and features are available to make specifying the target easier and more flexible.</content></Contents>
<topic name="area"><Contents><content type="text">area syntax: 'area:[type]:range'

Used to run a command on all entities of a specific type within a range. (crosses portals; range doesn't include yourself)
Available types are players (default), actors, npcs, items, and entities. (no spaces before/after colons) Note that this is a very powerful feature; be careful!
Examples: "/info area:entities:30" lists info on everything within 30m,
"/modify area:items:10 remove" deletes all litter within 10m,
"/teleport area:players:5 hydlaa_plaza" teleports you and all players within 5m to the plaza.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="here"><Contents><content type="text">keyword 'here'

Used to specify your current sector for sector based commands. Also may be used as a destination for /teleport to indicate your exact location. Examples: "/thunder here", "/teleport target here".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="IDs"><Contents><content type="text">ID syntax: 'pid:#' and 'eid:#'

Targets and destinations may be specified by either player/character ID (PID) or entity ID (EID). (no spaces before/after colon) IDs may be obtained via the /info command. Note that while PIDs do not change, EIDs do. Example: "/teleport eid:42 here".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="names"><Contents><content type="text">

Targets and destinations with more than one word in them must be specified using quotes, for most commands. Full names must be used for NPCs and items; only first names are needed for players. In the case of non-unique names, it will simply use the first it finds. Example: /teleport me "Grok Idon".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="me"><Contents><content type="text">keyword 'me'

Used to target yourself for a command. Example:  "/slide me F".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="target"><Contents><content type="text">keyword 'target'

Used to act on your currently selected entity with a command. In commands that only need one parameter, this keyword is implicit. Also supported as a destination for /teleport. Example: "/mute target" or simply "/mute".</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<topic name="/action"><Contents><content type="text">Action location commands.
To create a new action location entrance:
/action create_entrance [sector_name] [description]</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/admin"><Contents><content type="text">/admin

Resets your admin level.  Lists and allows you to use various GM/admin commands.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/assignfaction"><Contents><content type="text">/assignfaction [me/target/eid/pid/area/name] [factionname] [points]

Awards the player of a positive or negative faction points for a particular faction.
factionname is the name of the faction of which the player is being changed
points can be negative or positive and it's relative to the current player faction points.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/award"><Contents><content type="text">/award [target|pid:&lt;PID&gt;|area:type:range[:name]|me|&lt;player name&gt;|eid:&lt;EID&gt;|&lt;focus select a target&gt;] REWARD &lt;reward specific values&gt;

Reward
To give experience use - exp &lt;value&gt;
/award harnquist exp 100

To give an item use - item &lt;count&gt; &lt;item&gt;
/award harnquist item 1 apple

To give skill levels - skill &lt;skill name&gt;|all [+/-]&lt;value&gt;
/award harnquist skill cooking +1

To give money - money &lt;circles|hexa|octas|trias&gt; &lt;value&gt;|random
/award harnquist money circles 1

To give faction - faction &lt;faction name&gt; &lt;value&gt;
/award harnquist 'Red Order' 5

To give practice points - practice &lt;skill name&gt;|all &lt;value&gt;
/award harnquist practice cooking 10
</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/awardexp"><Contents><content type="text">/awardexp target value

Awards progression points to a player for the completion of a GM run event. (enter a negative value to take away PP).</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/badtext"><Contents><content type="text">/badtext [first entry] [last entry]

Shows what was told to the targeted npc and couldn't be understand by it.
First and last entry must be defined and last entry must be greater than first entry.
Example: /badtext 1 10 shows the latest 10 entries</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/ban"><Contents><content type="text">/ban name minutes hours days [IP] reason
OR /ban name [IP] reason

Bans a player from logging into the game for a specified amount of time.  (default is 2 days)  'Name' may be a character name, an account name, or an account number.  A reason must be specified. If IP is specified the ip will be banned as well. Note that the optional switch [IP] above indicates optional inclusion of the letters "ip" in the command to have the IP address also banned.  Do NOT type a full IP Address in the command.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/banadvisor"><Contents><content type="text">/banadvisor name

Bans a player from advising until /unbanadvisor is used.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/banname"><Contents><content type="text">/banname name

Bans a name from use in character creation.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/changeguildleader"><Contents><content type="text">/changeguildleader [new leader] [guildname]

Change the guilds leader.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/changeguildname"><Contents><content type="text">/changeguildname

Change the selected guilds name.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/changename"><Contents><content type="text">/changename [me/target/eid/pid/area/old name] [force|forceall] new name [new lastname]

Changes the player's name. If force is given, the last name doesn't have to be unique. If forceall is given the first name and last name don't have to be unique. If the lastname is not given the lastname will be preseved. If 'no' is given as lastname, the lastname will be removed.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/changenpctype"><Contents><content type="text">/changenpctype [me/target/eid/pid/area/old name] [&lt;brain&gt;|reload]

Changes the brain of the selected npcs. Use reload to reload the npctype db and set the new brain for the npc. Only the selected npc will have the reloaded brain set.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/charlist"><Contents><content type="text">/charlist [me/target/eid/pid/area/name]

Informs the GM of the IDs and names of all characters on the same account as the account of the given character.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/checkitem"><Contents><content type="text">/checkitem [target] [quantity|''] [item|tria]

Commands used to check the presence of an item in another character.  Example: "/checkitem Bob 42 tria".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/crystal"><Contents><content type="text">/crystal [interval] [max random interval modifier] [amount] [range] [item]

Create a new hunt location which spawns an item in interval + random secs up to a max of amount within the range.
Notice: The intervals are in seconds, not milliseconds.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/death"><Contents><content type="text">/death name

Kills something.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/debugnpc"><Contents><content type="text">/debugnpc [target/eid/pid/area/name] [&lt;debug level&gt;]

Changes the debug level of the selected npcs.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/debugtribe"><Contents><content type="text">/debugtribe [target/eid/pid/area/name] [&lt;debug level&gt;]

Changes the debug level of the tribe for the selected npcs.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/deletechar"><Contents><content type="text">/deletechar [character name] [petitioner name]
OR /deletechar pid:#

Deletes a character on the same account as the specified petitioner's.  (petition fraud check)  A player or NPC may also be specified by player ID.  (no checks done for players; unique/master NPCs may not be deleted by this method).</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/deputize"><Contents><content type="text">/deputize player level

Temporarily changes a character's access level to player, tester, GM, GM1-GM5, or developer.  Used to give GMs abilities needed for special instances, or to temporarily add a player to a testers group.  May also be used to demote yourself to a player's status for testing.  (temp level expires on logout, and may be reset by anyone via "/deputize me reset").</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/divorce"><Contents><content type="text">/divorce name

Divorce a character from another one if they are married.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/disablequest"><Contents><content type="text">/disablequest questname [save]

This function will toggle the quest from enabled to disabled status and viceversa, if the save flag is used the new status will also be saved in the database.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/event"><Contents><content type="text">Administer events.
To create a new event, a GM should enter:
/event create [name] [description]

To register all players in range, or a player by name, the GM should enter (note, [player] can be by name, or by target):
/event register [range 0-100 | player]

The GM can remove a player from a current event by (note, [player] can be by name, or by target):
/event remove [player]

When an event is complete, the GM should enter:
/event complete

To reward the participants (all of them, those within a specified range or an individual - by name or by target) of a current event:
/event reward [range 0-100 | all | player] # [item name]
[item name] can be "exp" (experience) where # Progression Points are awarded.
[item name] can be "faction [faction name]" to adjust the faction standing.
NOTE: Exp is in PP not in experience, differently from awardexp and givekillexp

If a GM wants to assume control of an ongoing event, because the original GM character has been deleted, or has abandoned it and is offline, the GM can enter:
/event control [name]

A completed event can be totally discarded by a GM; either by using the 'Discard' button in the Quest/Event Notebook, or by the following command. A GM can discard a completed event of another GM as long as that GM is offline at the time. NOTE: the event will be totally erased from the game and cannot be undone.
/event discard [name]</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/freeze"><Contents><content type="text">/freeze player

Prevents a player from moving or using any commands until they quit/relog.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/fog"><Contents><content type="text">/fog sector [density [[r g b] length fade]|stop]

It creates fog effect in a specific sector, with a specific density (0-255), the rgb values of the effect (0-255), its fading
value (in milliseconds) used for fading in and fading out, and the overall length of the effect in msec. If length is 0, the effect is permanent.
With specified sector, it starts fog with default values: density 200, fade 10000 msec, length 0, soft white color(r 200, g 200, w 200).
Use /fog sector off or /fog sector -1 for resetting.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/giveitem"><Contents><content type="text">/giveitem [target] [quantity|'all'|''] [item|tria]

Commands used to transfer an item from you to another character.  Example: "/giveitem Bob Apple".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/guard"><Contents><content type="text">/guard [target] [off]

This command allows you to guard or unguard any item in the world. You just have to provide a target (which can be an area, an eid of the currently selected target. If no other parameter is provided it will toggle guard status on the item.
NOTE: If you make an item guarded you will be the one guarding it.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/impersonate"><Contents><content type="text">/impersonate name command message

Talk as if you are 'name'. Command can be say, shout, or worldshout. If you use the keyword 'text' for name it will produce a message similar to /me within the command's range.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/info"><Contents><content type="text">/info target [summary|all|help]

Reports available information on an object/NPC/player (may be offline):  player ID from the database, account ID, IP address, total time connected, and item flags/spawn info.  Use this for bug reports about any stuck/glitched item/NPC/player.

Summary and All give GMs possibility to extract different information about NPCs.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/inspect"><Contents><content type="text">/inspect target

Prints the inventory of the specified NPC or player.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/item"><Contents><content type="text">/item name [random|quality value]

Creates a new object from the named item at your current location.  With no name specified, it opens the item spawn GUI.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/key"><Contents><content type="text">Administrator key commands.
To change the lock on a the targeted item.  This removes ability to unlock target from all keys:
/key changelock

Make a key out of item in right hand:
/key make

Make a master key out of item in right hand:
/key makemaster

Copy key item in hand:
/key copy

Clear all locks the key in hand can open:
/key clearlocks

Add to the key in hand the ability to lock targeted item:
/key addlock

Remove from the key in hand the ability to lock targeted item:
/key removelock

Take the key in hand and make or unmake it into a skeleton key that will open any lock, if you have a security level greater than 'player':
/key skel</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/kick"><Contents><content type="text">/kick name reason

Kicks the named player off of the server.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/killnpc"><Contents><content type="text">/killnpc [me/target/eid/pid/area/name] [&lt;damge&gt;|reload]

Kills the targeted NPC, using the current target if no name is given. The reload option recreates the NPC with stats and triggers from the DB.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/listwarnings"><Contents><content type="text">/listwarnings [me/target/eid/pid/area/name]
List all warnings given to the targeted account.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/loadquest"><Contents><content type="text">/loadquest questname

Reloads the given quest.
Note that you might need to wrap it like this \"quest name\" in case the quest name has spaces.</content></Contents></topic>
<branch name="/location"><Contents><content type="text">Online edit of locations. Location is used by the NPCClient to locate areas needed for their behaviors.

/location add
/location adjust
/location display
/location hide
/location info
/location insert
/location list
/location radius
/location show</content></Contents>
<topic name="/location add"><Contents><content type="text">/location add &lt;type&gt; &lt;name&gt; &lt;radius&gt; [&lt;rotation angle&gt;]

Add a new location. For a list of types use the /location list command.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/location adjust"><Contents><content type="text">/location adjust

Adjust the position of the nearest location to your position.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/location display|show"><Contents><content type="text">/location display|show

Display all locations in current sector.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/location hide"><Contents><content type="text">/location hide

Hide all locations in current sector.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/location info"><Contents><content type="text">/location info

Display info about nearest location in current sector.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/location insert"><Contents><content type="text">/location insert

Insert a new point after current selected point region.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/location list"><Contents><content type="text">/location list

List all location types.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/location radius"><Contents><content type="text">/location radius &lt;radius&gt; &lt;search radius&gt;

Adjust the radius of the location nearest current position.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/location select"><Contents><content type="text">/location select &lt;search radius&gt;

Select a point in a region.</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<topic name="/managepetitions"><Contents><content type="text">/managepetitions

Manage petitions to help users.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/marriageinfo"><Contents><content type="text">/marriageinfo [me/target/eid/pid/area/name]

View the details of a characters marriage.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/modify"><Contents><content type="text">/modify [target OR eid:#] [action] [setting(s)]

Alters the settings for an item.  Allowed actions:

'intervals' followed by 2 integer values for the interval and max modifier for spawning this item (must already spawn)

'amount' followed by an integer for the amount of items to spawned (must already spawn)

'range' followed by the range in which the items should spawn (must already spawn)

'remove' deletes this item and its spawn if it has one

'pickskill' followed by the name of a skill allows to change the skill required to pick the lock of the item. Use none to remove it.

'picklevel' followed by the level required of the currently set skill in order to be able to pick the lock of the item

'pickupable' followed by 'true' or 'false' sets the pickupable flag [This is only usable by developers]

'pickupableweak' followed by 'true' or 'false' sets the pickupableweak flag [This is the GM version of the flag]

'unpickable' followed by 'true' or 'false' sets the unpickable flag

'transient' followed by 'true or 'false' sets the transient flag (transient items auto-delete in ~3 hours)

'npcowned' followed by 'true' or 'false' sets the npcowned flag

'move' followed by x, y, z and optionally y-rotation coordinates

'collide' - enable/disable collision detection for that item.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/morph"><Contents><content type="text">/morph [target] [mesh name] [scale]

Changes the model used for a player until logout.  Use 'reset' in place of the mesh name to reset the mesh.  Do "/morph list" to see the full list of available meshes.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/mute"><Contents><content type="text">/mute player

Mutes the named player until they log back in to this server.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/npc"><Contents><content type="text">/npc [master npc name]

Creates a clone of the named NPC at your current location.</content></Contents></topic>
<branch name="/path"><Contents><content type="text">Online edit of paths

/path adjust
/path alias
/path display|show
/path flagclear
/path flagset
/path format
/path hide
/path help
/path info
/path move
/path point
/path remove
/path rename
/path select
/path split
/path start
/path stop|end

To create a path you need to do the following commands:
1) /path format &lt;format&gt;
2) /path start &lt;radius&gt;
3) /path point add (Any number of times)
4) /path stop &lt;radius&gt;</content></Contents>
<topic name="/path adjust"><Contents><content type="text">/path adjust [&lt;search radius&gt;]

Adjust the position of the nearest path point to your current position.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path alias"><Contents><content type="text">/path alias [add|remove|rotation] &lt;alias&gt; [&lt;rotation angle&gt;]

Add or remove a alias to/from the nearest waypoint. When adding you can specify a rotation angle in degrees for the alias. NPC client can use that to direct the NPC in the given direction when a NPC stop at the Waypoint.

Examples: /path alias remove "my alias"
          /path alias add "my new alias" 90</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path display|show"><Contents><content type="text">/path display|show [Points|Waypoints]

Display all waypoints and points unless either points or waypoints is specified. In that case only points or waypoints are displayed.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path flagclear"><Contents><content type="text">/path flagclear &lt;flag&gt; [&lt;search radius&gt;]

Clear flags on the nearest waypoint.

Supported flags are:
ALLOW_RETURN
UNDERGROUND
UNDERWATER
PRIVATE
PUBLIC
CITY
INDOOR
PATH
ROAD
GROUND

Use radius to narrow or widen the search for the waypoint. Use /path info to view current set flags.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path flagset"><Contents><content type="text">/path flagset [wp|path] &lt;flag&gt; [&lt;search radius&gt;]

Set flags on the nearest waypoint(wp) or path(path).

Supported flags are:
ALLOW_RETURN
UNDERGROUND
UNDERWATER
PRIVATE
PUBLIC
CITY
INDOOR

Use radius to narrow or widen the search for the waypoint. Use /path info to view current set flags.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path format"><Contents><content type="text">/path format &lt;format&gt; [first]

Set up the format to be used for waypoint name when creating new waypoints. Use /path format wp%03d 10 to create waypoints with name wp010, wp011,... First waypoint will be added when /path start is used in an location where there are no waypoint from before.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path help"><Contents><content type="text">/path help [sub command]

Display a short summary of commands or detailed syntax for a sub command if given.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path hide"><Contents><content type="text">/path hide [Points|Waypoints]

Hide all points. If waypoints or points are specified only either points or waypoints are hidden.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path info"><Contents><content type="text">/path info [&lt;search radius&gt;]

Show info about the nearest path or waypoint.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path move"><Contents><content type="text">/path move [wp|point] &lt;id&gt;|&lt;name&gt;

Move the waypoint or path point to your current position.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path point"><Contents><content type="text">/path point [add|insert|remove]

Add, insert or remove a point to or from the current selected path at your position.

A path will be automatically be selected on the /path start command. You could use the /path select command as well to select a new path.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path remove"><Contents><content type="text">/path remove [&lt;search radius&gt;]

Remove the nearest path. Use /path info to view information about the path that will be deleted.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path rename"><Contents><content type="text">/path rename &lt;name&gt; [&lt;search radius&gt;]

Rename the nearest waypoint or path. Use /path info to view information about the path that will be renamed. If both a path and a waypoint is inn range the waypoint will be the target.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path select"><Contents><content type="text">/path select &lt;search radius&gt;

Select the nearest path to be your current path. You need a select path to use /path point.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path split"><Contents><content type="text">/path split &lt;radius&gt; [WP flags]

Split a path into two paths inserting a new waypoint with name according to whats set with /path format.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path start"><Contents><content type="text">/path start &lt;radius&gt; [WP flags] [Path flags]

Start a new path. If there are a waypoint nearby the waypoint is used to start the path. Otherwise a new waypoint is created.

Supported WP flags are:
ALLOW_RETURN
UNDERGROUND
UNDERWATER
PRIVATE
PUBLIC
CITY
INDOOR
PATH
ROAD
GROUND

Supported Path flags are:
ONEWAY
NO_WANDER
TELEPORT</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/path stop|end"><Contents><content type="text">/path stop|end &lt;radius&gt; [WP flags]

Stop the current path. If there are a waypoint nearby the waypoint is used to end the path. Otherwise a new waypoint is created.</content></Contents></topic></branch>
<topic name="/percept"><Contents><content type="text">/percept [target|pid:&lt;PID&gt;|&lt;npc name&gt;|eid:&lt;EID&gt;] [perception] [type]

Send a perception to the selected NPC. Use /info to gain information about available reactions.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/pickup"><Contents><content type="text">/pickup [eid/area]

GM have an enhanced version of /pickup which supports also eid and area arguments.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/pos"><Contents><content type="text">/pos target

GMs have an enhanced version of the /pos command which shows your current region and the direction you are facing.  It also has an optional parameter to get the position of another entity.  (may specify by name or an ID)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/quest"><Contents><content type="text">/quest [me/target/eid/pid/area/name] [list|discard|complete|assign]

Manage completion of quests for the targeted player, or your own if you aren't targeting anyone.

/quest list [target]
/quest list [target] [quest name]
lists quest completion status for all quests and quest steps, or specific quests.

/quest discard [target] [quest name]
/quest discard [target] [quest name step x]
This will discard a quest or quest or quest step.

/quest assign [target] [quest name]
/quest assign [target] [quest name step x]
This will assign a quest or quest or quest step.

/quest complete [target] [quest name]
/quest compelte [target] [quest name step x]
This will complete a quest or quest or quest step.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/rain"><Contents><content type="text">/rain sector [drops [length [fade]]|stop]

It creates rain effect in a specific sector, with a specific number of drops, the length of the effect (in milliseconds) and its fading
value (in milliseconds).
With specified sector, it starts rain with default values: density 4000 drops, length 10 minutes and 10 seconds of fade.
The maximum number of drops allowed is 8000.
Use /rain sector 0 0 0 or /rain sector off for ending the event. </content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/reload"><Contents><content type="text">/reload [item|serveroptions|mathscript|path|locations]

Reloads entities from the database. Item reload the currently targeted item from the database. For serveroptions, mathscript, path, and locations
all data is reloaded.</content></Contents></topic>

<topic name="/scale"><Contents><content type="text">/scale [value]

This set the scale of the GM, this will change the size of the GM based on the value.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/runscript"><Contents><content type="text">/runscript [script_name] [me/target/eid/pid/area/name]

Runs a progression script on the target.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/set"><Contents><content type="text">/set target gm|player|attribute [on|off]

Many of these attribute are enabled by default for GMs.
If you do not specify on or off the current mode will be toggled.
You can also do "/set me list" to view your current attributes.

Available attributes are:
- invincible
- invisible
- viewall (see invisibles)
- nevertired
- nofalldamage
- infiniteinventory
- questtester (bypass quest lockouts and prerequisites).
- instantcast (bypasses spell casting time)
- givekillexp (awards experience when a GM is killed, as in an event)
- buddyhide (hides you from player (not GM/Dev) buddy lists)

To set the default used for players do "/set me player". For the default for GMs do "/set me gm".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/setlabelcolor"><Contents><content type="text">/setlabelcolor [target] [npc|player|tester|gm|gm1|dead|alive|normal]

Set the color of the label of target to the given value. The normal setting will again display the targets normal label color.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/setitemname"><Contents><content type="text">/setitemname [target/eid/area/original name] [name] [description]

Allows changing the name and description of the targeted item. Description is optional.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/setkillexp"><Contents><content type="text">/setkillexp [target] [exp amount]

Allows to set the experience (not measured in PP) the target will give to who kills him.
This command is temporary. Target is optional.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/setquality"><Contents><content type="text">/setquality [target/eid/area/name] [quality] [max quality]

Allows changing the quality of the targeted item. Max quality is optional.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/setskill"><Contents><content type="text">/setskill [target] [skill|'all'] [value|-1]

Set one of your or target's skills or stats to a specific value.  Use 'all' as the name to set all skills and stats to the given value. Use -1 for value if you would like to view the current value of a skill or stat. If no value is given 100 will be used as default.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/setstackable"><Contents><content type="text">/setstackable [on|off|reset|info]

Enables or disables the ability to stack the targeted item. Info will give the current status of this flag. Reset returns the item to the default stack mode for the item.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/settrait"><Contents><content type="text">/settrait [[target] [trait] | list [race] [gender]]

Allows changing the traits of a character.
Use "/settrait list [race] [gender]" to list all available traits for given race and gender.
Note: The adequate gender for Krans is "none".</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/show gm"><Contents><content type="text">/show gm

Shows the GM GUI, a window with a player list and quick access to many commands.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/slide"><Contents><content type="text">/slide target direction distance

Slides the target object/NPC/player in the direction specified (L,R,F,B,U,D,T,I). Moves one space or the distance specified.
The "direction" 'T' turns the target.  (in degrees; default is 90)
The "direction" 'I' changes target instance. (it's relative to current instance)</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/snow"><Contents><content type="text">/snow sector [flakes [length [fade]]|stop]

It creates snow effect in a specific sector, with a specific number of flakes, the length of the effect (in milliseconds) and its fading
value (in milliseconds).
With specified sector, it starts snow with default values: density 4000 flakes, length 10 minutes and 10 seconds of fade.
The maximum number of flakes allowed is 8000.
Use /snow sector 0 or /snow sector off for ending the event.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/takeitem"><Contents><content type="text">/takeitem [target] [quantity|'all'|''] [item|tria]

Command used to transfer an item to you from another character.  Example: "/takeitem target 3 Sabre"</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/teleport"><Contents><content type="text">/teleport &lt;subject&gt; &lt;destination&gt;

Move the subject to the given destination.

Subject might be one of the following:
me - Subject is you
target - Subject is your current target
&lt;object name&gt; - Subject is a named object
&lt;NPC name&gt; - Subject is the named NPC
&lt;player name&gt; - Subject is the named player
pid:&lt;PID&gt; - Subject is the player/npc with the given pid
eid:&lt;EID&gt; - Subject is the entity with the given eid.

Destination might be one of the following:
here [&lt;instance&gt;] - Your current position possible in another instance.
there &lt;instance&gt; - Their current position in another instance.
last - Last position
spawn - Spawn position
restore - Teleport offline character here
map [&lt;map name&gt;|here &lt;x&gt; &lt;y&gt; &lt;z&gt; [&lt;instance&gt;] - Map coordinates.

Examples:
   "/teleport target here"
   "/teleport me Bob"
   "/teleport me map npcroom"
   "/teleport me map hydlaa_plaza 3 -42 10"
   "/teleport "Ink and Paper" map here -234.11 2.23 832"</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/thaw"><Contents><content type="text">/thaw player

Disable the effect of the /freeze command on a player.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/thunder"><Contents><content type="text">/thunder [sector]

It creates a thunder and a lightning in the specified sector. If you don't specify the sector, it will try to create it in the
sector where you are, if it supports lightning.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/unban"><Contents><content type="text">/unban name

Remove the ban on a player, allowing them to log in again.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/unbanadvisor"><Contents><content type="text">/unbanadvisor name

Remove the advisor ban on a player, allowing them to advise again.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/unbanname"><Contents><content type="text">/unbanname name

Unban a name and makes it available for use again in character creation</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/unmute"><Contents><content type="text">/unmute player

Unmute the named player.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/updaterespawn"><Contents><content type="text">/updaterespawn [me/target/eid/pid/area/name] [here]

Set the targeted actor's respawn point to their current location. If 'here' is specified then the GM's current location will be used instead of the NPC's.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/warn"><Contents><content type="text">/warn target message

Send a warning message to a player in big, red, un-ignorable text on their screen and in all chat tabs.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/weather"><Contents><content type="text">/weather sector [on|off]

Turn on or off automatic weather for a sector.</content></Contents></topic>
<topic name="/targetname"><Contents><content type="text">/targetname [me/target/eid/pid/area/name]

Get the name of all the targeted objects.</content></Contents></topic></branch></help>
<!-- These commands are missing a topic (updated r2512):
study
tellnpcinternal
write -->
<!--- example to use for icons: <content type="pic" src="ButtonLook;ButtonOpen;ButtonPush" align="0" width="200" height="200" padding="20"/> -->


